<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vindication of free-grace: in opposition to this Arminian position, (Naturall men may do such things as whereunto God hath by way of promise annexed grace and acceptation.) / First preached, after asserted at Stephens Coleman-steete [sic] London, by Mr. John Goodvvin. Also an appendix proving the souls enjoying Christ after death, afore the Resurrection, against some errours hereafter specified. Published for the justification of truth by S.L.</title>
            <author>Lane, Samuel.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 208 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88635</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L341</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E275_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209881</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868732</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868732</idno>
            <idno type="VID">121088</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88635)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 121088)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 46:E275[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vindication of free-grace: in opposition to this Arminian position, (Naturall men may do such things as whereunto God hath by way of promise annexed grace and acceptation.) / First preached, after asserted at Stephens Coleman-steete [sic] London, by Mr. John Goodvvin. Also an appendix proving the souls enjoying Christ after death, afore the Resurrection, against some errours hereafter specified. Published for the justification of truth by S.L.</title>
                  <author>Lane, Samuel.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 72 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Macock, for Michael Spark junior, and are to be sold at the Blue Bible in Gren Arbour.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>S.L. = Samuel Lane, whose name appears on leaf A3r.</note>
                  <note>The sentence in title "Naturall men may do such things as whereunto God hath by way of promise annexed grace and acceptation" is printed between square brackets.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "April 1st".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Grace (Theology) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Arminianism --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:121088:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A VINDICATION OF FREE-GRACE: IN Oppoſition to this <hi>Arminian</hi> Poſition, <hi>[Naturall Men may do ſuch things as whereunto God hath by way of Promiſe annexed Grace and Acceptation.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt Preached, after Aſſerted At <hi>Stephens</hi> Coleman-ſteete <hi>London,</hi> BY M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> JOHN GOODVVIN.</p>
            <p>Alſo an Appendix proving the ſouls enjoying Chriſt after death, afore the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, againſt ſome errours hereafter ſpecified.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed for the juſtification of Truth BY <hi>S. L.</hi>
            </p>
            <bibl>13. Article of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </bibl>
            <q>
               <p>Works done before the Grace of Chriſt and the inſpiration of his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, do not make men meet to receive Grace.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>John Macock,</hi> for <hi>Michael Spark</hi> junior, and are to be ſold at the Blue Bible in <hi>Green Arbour.</hi> 1645.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prefatory_letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:121088:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:121088:2"/>
            <head>To the much eſteemed the Auditory of Maſter <hi>Iohn Goodwin,</hi> increaſe of grace be multiplyed to the compleating of Chriſts ſtature in you.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Greatly beloved in Chriſt,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Uch is the peculiarity of mine obligements to that perſon ſo Worthy, who under God hath the immediate power over me as would not tolerate my ſeeking out any beſides, to whom to commend this enſuing Treatiſe, were it not for this reaſon, becauſe I would not ſeem in the leaſt to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage a perſon ſo eminent, in a buſineſſe ſo perſonall. And amongſt you who may ſeem, and that rightly, in the eyes of others to be as a Garden of many excellent flowers, whereof 'tis hard to pick the faireſt: ſo choiſe are mine ingagements to ſome, as would render my perſonall choiſe moſt eaſie to whom in ſpeciall to recommend the ſame. But as I have ſhunned advice from any one, or more, that have been, or are of the whole Auditory, ſo I chooſe humbly to tender it to the whole promiſcuouſly; that ſo without leaſt prejudice all may unanimouny con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire in this deſigne of propagating the truth. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, that I ſuffer not through your miſ-conſtruction, I have next hereto annexed a <hi>Breviat</hi> of the grounds of my publiſhing hereof. Concerning which matter, as I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly crave your excuſing the rudeneſſe and prolixity of the former <hi>Letter</hi> enſuing, the rather, becauſe (though 'twas framed very ſuddenly) I chooſe to print the exact Copy of that which I gave in to Mr. <hi>Goodwin,</hi> thereby to prevent ſuſpicions of wrong or miſtake, rather then make an amendment thereof. So touching my <hi>Reply</hi> I alſo crave pardon for my boldneſſe, in undertaking an enterprize ſo weighty; becauſe (all other wayes and means of vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion aſſayed being fruſtrated) I deem it meet for truth to be in ſome meaſure vindicated, though in a weak and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy manner, by that very rude pen which hath unwit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly
<pb facs="tcp:121088:3"/>been rendred injurious thereunto. And though I muſt needs acknowledge this work of mine to be limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by moſt unhappy confines, not only as it ſingles out unto me that perſon to deale with, whom I highly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect; but alſo as it points out an Auditory ſo able and judicious to whom to commend it: (w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> I ſpeak not out of flattery but to the glory of Gods grace in you) yet as on the one hand the competition being not between man and man, but man and truth according to that impartiall verdit <hi>Amicus Plato, amicus Socrates, ſed magis amica veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas;</hi> 'tis no hard matter to determine which of the twaine to prefer: ſo on the other hand, for as much as there is now no ſure or probable way left, ſtanding in competi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with this made choice of; I thence conclude a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of proſecuting this way, though ſo unworthy of your acceptance. Wherein you may pleaſe further to conſider that I trouble you not with needleſſe diſputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: but this high queſtion whether the tearms of the Goſpel be free or mercenary, which being the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our faith, is a controverſie juſtified, <hi>Iude</hi> 3. After which I have in the cloſe alleaged ſome reaſons againſt three errors there ſpecified; which I the rather humbly commend to your view; becauſe there be that conceive the ſubſtance of the two former, was publickly delivered in <hi>Crooked-Lane</hi> London, in a Funerall Sermon diverſe moneths agoe: and that probably before many of you, but by whom I ſhall not ſo much as name, ſuppoſing the known miſchief of theſe errours to be a ſufficient motive to this work: Through all which, that God would guide you to weigh this matter in the ballance of the Sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; that rightly dividing this work to the judgement and affections, both may performe their reſpective offices without uſurpation, and ſo conduct you to the deſired Goale; the truth, is the prayer of him who remains,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in humble meekneſſe, truth, and love, <hi>S. L.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:121088:3"/>
            <head>A Breviate of ſuch ſpecial proceedings with <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> John Goodwin</hi> as may ſufficiently evince the neceſsity of publiſhing the ſequell.</head>
            <p>NOt to mention the former paſſages being Epitomized in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the enſuing Reply; I diverſe moneths paſt, deſired him to take ſome time to examine this matter, and having his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe that I ſhould have notice of his firſt leiſure, I contented my ſelf her with for ſundry moneths: after which I renued my former re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, <hi>Jan.</hi> 2. 1644. whereto receiving this Anſwer, that I ſhould have notice of his firſt leiſure, by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>John Price,</hi> I contented my ſelf with this alſo, till neceſſity forced me to commend to him this fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Motion.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THe drift of your laſt words to me</hi> (Jan. 2. 1644.) <hi>being to put me in expectation of your pre-fixing a time for your peruſing my Reply to your Sermon, which time you promiſed to make known to my Loving friend</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> John Price, <hi>I accordingly expected the ſame, and notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding my knowledge of his long abſence from</hi> London, <hi>I was deſirous to forbear the renuing of my deſire till his return; but there is ſuch an alteration now in hand, touching my proper conditiou, as that I am ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitated without any delay to addreſſe my ſelf to you, humbly deſiring your peruſall of the ſaid Reply: And that both becauſe the next week will be inconvenient becauſe of the Faſt, and alſo that I conceive that my condition afterwards will not permit any longer delay. My deſire therefore is, That you would be pleaſed to take ſome time this week for view thereof, that I may know your mind concerning this matter; Of which I pray be pleaſed to return a certain Anſwer to my loving friend</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> William Milner, <hi>whom I make bold withall at the preſent, becauſe I have a buſineſſe of much importance to tranſact this day; and if I may understand that you will pick out a time this week, ſo as that I may know your mind in it, I ſhall this morning bring or ſend the Reply to you, ſealed up: Otherwiſe I conceive I muſt neceſſarily conſider upon ſome way of Vindicating the truth, whether by publiſhing, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, whereto craving your Anſwer, I reſt</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Coleman-ſtreet <date>
                           <hi>Feb.</hi> 18. 1644.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
                  <trailer>for Mr <hi>John Goodwin.</hi>
                  </trailer>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Yours in humility, truth, &amp; love. SAM. LANE.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>IN Anſwer whereto he prefixed next Thurſday's Even, <hi>Feb.</hi> 20. the day before which I meeting him deſired him to diſpence with mine abſence the time prefixed, becauſe of ſome ſpeciall occaſions, and in lieu of my comming, to accept of ſome friends to be with him,
<pb facs="tcp:121088:4"/>whereto he willingly conſenting; accordingly Mr. <hi>Thomas Weaver</hi> and another ſpeciall friend of mine were preſent, and read a good part of the Reply: whereto the ſubſtance of his Anſwer was, <hi>The he did not hold, nor go about to prove that God is bound to give g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> upon mans endeavours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which Anſwer ſo expreſly denying the direct tendency of the firſt errour oppoſed, and of the following Sermon (both ſtrictly concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning naturall mens power towards attaining grace) puts me out of all expectation of his publike Vindication of that truth, which he thus denies to have at all oppoſed. Now foraſmuch as the firſt enſuing <hi>Letter,</hi> though <hi>privately</hi> commended, hath occaſioned the <hi>publike</hi> preaching of the Sermon following, wherein the Covenant of Free-Grace is bitterly reproached; there appears hence a great neceſſity of <hi>publike</hi> vindication thereof. And yet for a more orderly juſtification, I ſhall declare, firſt, ſuch teſtimonies as evidence M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>John Goodwins</hi> maintaining that errour: ſecondly, why his maintaining thereof ſhould be publikely mentioned.</p>
            <p>The firſt of which particulars refers to two things,
<list>
                  <item>1. The Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies concerning his firſt delivery of that errour.</item>
                  <item>2. Thoſe that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern his Preaching of the enſuing Sermon.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>For the former ſort of which Teſtimones, I refer in ſpeciall to the three manuall Teſtimonies ſubſcribed to the extract next enſuing. Which extract twice together containes that errour. Beſides which I commended two Coppies more of the ſame extract to the peruſall of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Thomas Weaver,</hi> and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Thomas Ruddyard,</hi> two known exact writers, who both teſtified, <hi>That they found thoſe Coppies to be the ſubstance of what he then delivered.</hi> Yea M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Goodwin</hi> himſelf imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately after his Preaching the following Sermon told me he had read the firſt letter enſuing, (which chargeth him with that errour) not diſclaiming any jot thereof. All which Teſtimonies may be lookt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on not meerly as ſufficient, but alſo as ſuperfluous, if we obſerve the enſuing Sermon, in which the ſame errour is three times repeated, as in the Reply is after declared.</p>
            <p>And touching the Teſtimonies concerning the enſuing Sermon; Though I could not obtain M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Goodwins</hi> own Coppie, which I deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of him, yet I obtained a Coppie from M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Tho. Ruddyard;</hi> one, who by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Goodwins</hi> Teſtimony to me, was affirmed to be a very exact writer: Of which Coppie though I could not obtain M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wins</hi> Examination, which I alſo deſired; yet I obtained the examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of two exact writers, whoſe ſubſcribed Teſtimonies are hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:121088:4"/>affixed to that Sermon: Yea, I had alſo the verball Teſtimonies of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>John Price,</hi> and Mr <hi>Henry Brandrift,</hi> who upon peruſall affirmed, that they found it to be the ſame that Mr <hi>Goodwin</hi> delivered.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing to be proved is the neceſſity of publiſhing his maintaining the ſame. For which, I am not to declare how neceſſary it is that the following errours ſhould be publikely declaimed againſt, too ſadly known to be now moſt rife in this City; but more ſtrictly to ſhew how needfull 'tis to declare according to the enſuing Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Goodwins</hi> maintaining the ſame.</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe his diſputings upon this matter have been highly approved of by many: whereof divers give this Teſtimony, <hi>That he hath cut the hair between other Divines and the Arminians.</hi> Yea, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Goodwin</hi> told me he was much deſired to Print his diſputes againſt the <hi>Arminians,</hi> ſo highly are they eſteemed; in the laſt of which diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes, the enſuing errour was pleaded for.</p>
            <p>But ſecondly, and ſpecially whereas there are (as 'tis conceived) thouſands now amongſt us, who hold that grand errour, <hi>That God hath promiſed grace upon mans doing;</hi> two of that Sect, diſcourſing with a Reverend Divine of this City, told him, <hi>That in holding this Tenent, they held but that which Maſter John Goodwin maintaines,</hi> in whom they greatly glory. Now 'tis not eaſie to conceive how great miſchiefe the Preaching and arguing of ſo eminent a perſon for that errour may do to the confirming of men therein, eſpecially if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider how highly he hath gratified the maitainers thereof in another way alſo; as namely, by his earneſt pleading for a tolleration of any Sect whatſoever.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I might adde the conſideration of his ſo often preſſing that errour, not onely thee ſeverall Lords dayes, on the laſt of which the enſuing Sermon was wholy ſpent to maintain it; but alſo in ſome of his laſt exerciſes againſt the <hi>Arminians,</hi> in the laſt whereof the ſaid errour was pleaded for, both by that grand Argument, <hi>That God cannot in juſtice deſtroy man for not doing that which is altogether out of his power to do,</hi> and alſo that of <hi>Adams</hi> not having a power to beleeve. Which two Arguments are a great part of the Sermon enſuing: yea further it hath been often acknowledged by a known member of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Goodwins</hi> Church that about 7. years ago, he Preached the ſame matter, and that then divers able Divines of this City did af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Goodwin</hi> that he Preached Arminianiſm. Seeing then this errour together with its defenſive Arguments have been with gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t zeal ſo often inculcated for a more ſure and through diſtilling the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:121088:5"/>into the minds of the hearers, hence its neceſſary not onely to declaim againſt it, but <hi>tanquam digito monſtrare,</hi> ſo diſtinctly and directly to point it out, as that all ſuch hearers may have peculiar admoniſhment hereof, and that by mentioning the publiſher of it. Beſides which, other grounds might be urged, but I deſire to ſhun further prolixity herein, which nevertheleſſe I thought needfull to glance at, hereby to ſhew that it hath been mine endeavour ſo to fulfill the Law of truth, as not to tranſgreſſe the Law of that Chriſtian reverence and reſpect which is due unto him.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>S. L.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon_extracts">
            <head>An extract of ſome particulars in a Sermon of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>John Goodwin,</hi> of Aprill 12. 1644. which are ſcrupled.</head>
            <p>ONe particular whereof was a third motive he gave to naturall men on that Text 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.3. Which motive was, that if naturall men will but ingage themſelves withall within them to ſeek for this grace, they ſhall ſurely finde it, they ſhall not miſcarry in it; but cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly this grace ſhall be vouchſafed to them; which for proof were alleaged two Texts, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.7. &amp; <hi>John</hi> 6.37. Which was further pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted, by anſwering an Objection touching mans being dead in ſins and treſpaſſes: the fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th part of which anſwer was this. Fifthly, That men that are in ſuch a ſenſe dead in ſins and treſpaſſes, have a naturall life of reaſon, judgement, underſtanding, conſcience, &amp;c. in them: by reaſon of which excellent principles of nature, reaſon, &amp;c. Men are able to ponder upon ſuch wayes &amp; means propounded, and conceive them probable for that work; they are not ſo dead, but <hi>if they will gave out themſelves to do, they may do ſuch things whereunto God hath been graciouſly pleaſed to annex a promiſe of grace, there is a power in men to do ſuch things (if they will give it forth &amp; imploy it according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) as unto which things God hath by way of promiſe annexed grace and acceptation:</hi> for which, beſides thoſe Texts fore-mentioned, ſee <hi>Prov.</hi> 2.1, 2, 3. &amp; 10.6.27. and ſtrive to enter in at the ſtrait gate.</p>
            <div type="witness_statements">
               <p>One Copy whereof ſent Mr. <hi>Richard Atkins</hi> is thus ſubſcribed.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Sir,</hi> For the ſum and ſubstance you have drawn a true draught of that which <hi>Maſter Goodwin</hi> did deliver.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Yours to command <hi>Rich. Alkins.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>A ſecond Copy commended to Mr. <hi>Laurence Steele</hi> is thus ſubſcribed.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>I finde nothing in ſubſtance differing from my Copy, ſave only I finde not the two firſt Scriptures in this Sermon, but I ſuppoſe I have them in that before.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>L. Steele.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>A third Copy commended to Mr. <hi>Iohn weeks,</hi> is thu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſubſcribed.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Sir,</hi> I have peruſed this, and finde it in the main to agree with mine, only it was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered in more full expreſſions.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Yours <hi>John Weeks.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Which 3. Teſtimonies, as alſo thoſe two affixed to the enſuing Sermon, are left with <hi>Michael Spark ſenior,</hi> leaſt any calumniate the truth in the Authors abſence.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errat.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 56. <hi>line</hi> 7. <hi>for</hi> Goſpel <hi>reade</hi> groſſeſt.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="correspondence">
            <div n="1" type="letter">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:121088:5"/>
               <head>The firſt Letter to Maſter <hi>J. G.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Much Honoured Sir,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hether or no I poſſeſſe honourable and eminent thoughts of your ſelf, I ſhall refer you to thoſe expreſſions, which my Conſcience commanded me to dictate to you, before my going into the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, whereby you may judge; and becauſe the ground on which thoſe expreſſions of mine to you ward, was that of God which I ſaw in you; I know no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter way whereby to endeavour my retaining intirely my due eſteeme of you, then to deſire; That by, and in you, the ground thereof may continue firme, and immovable; which in mine eye ſeemes at preſent much to flag and ſtagger, and that from ſome aſſertions, which ſpecially the laſt Sabboth being <hi>April</hi> 14. 1644. I received from you therefore to prevent the leaſt beſieg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch an adverſary, whoſe heart lyes fair and open to me, as I well know by experience from that utterly undeſerved reſpect, I have found from you; I ſhall in the ſtrength of this preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion adventure rudely upon the work intended.</p>
               <p>Wherein I muſt neceſſarily content my ſelf, with ſignifying to you ſome particulars, which to me ſeem evidently lyable to exception, ſuſpending the leaſt taking notice of ſuch things, which poſſibly, on due conſideration may be found to require more exact ſcrutiny. Whereof as touching what I ſhall at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent mention, I muſt ſatisfie my ſelf to hint things in an indigeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and diſorderly manner; having been prevented by the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening of other unexpected occurrences, therefore for moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſeneſſe therein, though I count it my beſt courſe, to have extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted the ſubſtance of all, wherein I am unſatisfied, firſt intire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by it ſelf, yet I may not attempt that, but muſt onely name
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:121088:6"/>ſuch particulars of that kinde, Immediately before what I ſhall affirme in order, touching each one reſpectively: wherein not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring to depend on mine own Judgement onely, leaſt I might have miſtaken you, I by conference, finde ſome others do conceive you ſo to have delivered your ſelf in thoſe particulars, as I my ſelf conceive thereof.</p>
               <p>You may therefore remember, that the ſubſtance of <hi>your third motive to naturall men, in reference to their accepting of Grace,</hi> according to what you inſiſted upon, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.3. was to this effect, <hi>That if ſuch will but ingage themſelves, and all within them, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their naturall power, to ſeek for this Grace, they ſhall not miſcarry, but ſtirring up themſelves in good earnest to ſeek this Grace, they ſhall ſurely finde it:</hi> Which after your glancing at the <hi>Antinomians,</hi> you preſt more largely, and that by backing this motive with two Texts, <hi>John</hi> 6. <hi>v.</hi> 37. and <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p>Which Scriptures you alleadge, to prove, <hi>That if men improve their Naturall abilities to the utmoſt</hi> (which is the ſtrength of the motive) <hi>in ſeeking Grace, they ſhall finde it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Concerning which Texts I cannot as yet ſee any ſuch thing proved by them, for the former whereof, <hi>John</hi> 6.37. <hi>Whoſoever comes, &amp;c.</hi> This you underſtand indefinitely, whoſoever naturall man comes; And in what manner muſt he come? With, or in the ſtrength of his naturall abilities; ſuch a one Ile in no wiſe caſt out; which you acknowledge, imports affirmatively, I will accept, which might be proved to import ſo much from, <hi>John</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 40. Where <hi>life</hi> is annexed to <hi>comming.</hi> Now as touching this Text, 'tis true, that whoſoever being a naturall man, ſhall through the full improvement of naturall powers, ſo come to Chriſt, as is here meant, that is, after a ſaving manner, even with ſaving ſaith, which kinde of comming can onely carry life, as this here doth; Such a one aſſuredly ſhall not be caſt out by Chriſt, no more then he which doth the Law perfectly ſhall yet dye: for the Law will keep promiſe (though none can claim ought thence) namely, <hi>That the man that doth them, ſhall live in them;</hi> but this is far from proving, that a man by improving his naturalls ſhall come to Chriſt ſavingly by virtue thereof, no more then a man may do the Laws works, and live in them; concerning which <hi>Paul</hi> peremptorily and rationally concludes in that <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.11. That no man can live by virtue of his performing that Covenant: but there
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:121088:6"/>will be further occaſion miniſtred by what follows, whence to ſpeak further in reference to this place quoted, which was there but briefly touched for a proof of that, which it ſeems not in the leaſt to do.</p>
               <p>The next alledged is <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 7. and that for the ſame purpoſe to which muſt refer, as above; concerning which place 'tis moſt cleer, that that Text importing commands preſt, and promiſes an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed, are laid down in moſt generall tearms, therefore for the true underſtanding of the nature of our duty, or our right manner of performance thereof, we muſt conſult with other Scriptures where 'tis laid down more particularly, and not underſtand the words in a ſtrict literall ſence. That we muſt not underſtand it, as barely expreſt, without limitation or qualification, I prove from this; that other Scriptures gain-ſay ſuch a ſence, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s that <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.3. <hi>Ye aske and receive not,</hi> Why not? not for want of asking, they did aske, yet 'twas not given: ſo then, To all that aske it ſhall not be given; men may ſo aske as that their asking ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be given them, the default wherein may be double, from the end of their asking to ſatisfie luſts. But is that all? No, another default is the want of a due qualification in the asking, which is as neceſſary as Salvation it ſelf, and that is an asking in faith; ſo <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.6. in the fifth <hi>verſe,</hi> he gives out a promiſe indefinitely, <hi>If any of you:</hi> of whom? Naturall improvers? No, of you belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, for that he ſuppoſed in the third <hi>verſe, the trying of your faith,</hi> they had faith to try; let ſuch <hi>aske in faith,</hi> acting that power of faith, created by Gods Spirit in them; <hi>but let him aske in faith,</hi> let him not think it enough to aske in any faſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on, but onely in faith, which tearms, <hi>but</hi> and <hi>faith,</hi> exclude all oth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r <hi>ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi> from <hi>receiving:</hi> which is plainly expreſt in verſe 7. <hi>Let not that man think to receive,</hi> what man? that man whoſoever, be he ever ſo able to improve his naturall abilities in asking, as long as he askes without faith, let not ſuch a one think to receive, for 'tis to think the Scrpture lyes: if then this place quoted, will prove that naturall men improving themſelves in good earneſt in asking, ſhall hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, as you expreſly affirmed, then it follows (as I conceive) that a naturall man may by improving his own power, be inabled to aske in faith, for ſuch an asking onely is ſure to receive, but if we will take <hi>Pauls</hi> judgement, he affirms, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.9. <hi>That the power by which we beleeve, is</hi> not our own fully improved, but
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:121088:7"/>
                  <hi>that exceeding greatneſſe of power, which raiſed Chriſt from the dead:</hi> faith is by grace, and not naturall improvement; but you will ſay this is granted, that tis wrought by God; namely, upon naturall improvements: to which I reply, Tis true you expreſt that, but yet in theſe two quotations, you apply or rather ſubject (as I conceive) theſe promiſes under the power of naturall men, whom you make to have power in themſelves, to put themſelves under theſe Promiſes, and within the Covenant, elſe they could not be ſo certain, touching Gods performing them to themſelves; which to prove, you directly alleadged them; in which places there's no tittle of any ſuch promiſe, that upon their improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, God will give faith, and ſo they ſhall be accepted, and yet you undertake to prove, that they may ſo performe the condition on their ſide, as reciprocally to make God bound to receive them into his grace thereupon according to his promiſe.</p>
               <p>Further in reference to that, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.7. <hi>Aske, &amp;c.</hi> but how ſhall we aske? <hi>Iohn</hi> 15. <hi>verſe</hi> 16. <hi>Whatſoever ye doke in my Name, the Father will give, Acts</hi> 4. <hi>verſe</hi> 12. <hi>No name under heaven whereby to be ſaved,</hi> or <hi>no other power,</hi> Therefore no naturall, how ever improved, <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sk in my Name,</hi> not your own, but ſo long as we ask by the ſtrength of our naturall abilities, 'tis in our own name and power, and therefore ſhall not avail, becauſe not in Chriſts Name.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object </seg>
                  </label> But may not our naturall power be improved to ſuch height, as whereby, and whereupon God may be ingaged by virtue of them, to accept us in Chriſts Name?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw </seg>
                  </label> No, <hi>in no wiſe,</hi> for then ther's another name or power beſides Chriſts, which can ingage God, which would peremptorily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict the Scripture.</p>
               <p>Again, this injunction <hi>Aske and it ſhall be given,</hi> is chiefly directed to the Diſciples, for 'twas a part of that Sermon Preached to them in ſpeciall, as whereby they might the better know how to deal with the <hi>Iews,</hi> as the beginning of it ſhews, <hi>chap.</hi> 5. <hi>verſe</hi> 1, 2. Yea, the <hi>verſe</hi> immediately foregoing this under cenſure was primarily in reference to them; <hi>Give not that that's holy, Nor caſt your Pearls, &amp;c.</hi> They were then ſuch as had things that were <hi>holy,</hi> and <hi>pearls,</hi> yea to <hi>give,</hi> and <hi>cast;</hi> therefore ſuch who not onely had thoſe holy things, but had them as Stewards of the Treaſures of heaven, thereby directing them, to whom to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:121088:7"/>give them, to which the following promiſe, <hi>Aske and have,</hi> fitly belongs: but this liberty befits not a carnall one, 'tis ill truſting ſuch with ſuch large promiſes, who have no ſuch <hi>holy</hi> things or <hi>pearls,</hi> to <hi>give</hi> or <hi>cast.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to proceed, you on a fourth ſub-divided head, undertook to give out the meaning of that tearm, of <hi>being dead in trespaſſes and ſins,</hi> which you ſhewed, was meant of ſuch, as were voyd of all knowledge of God, not as onely being in a ſtate of condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, but in that they had no injoyment of the <hi>Spirit</hi> of God at all, nor of its workings, which works in ſome kinde alwayes where-ever the Goſpell is preached, <hi>Dead,</hi> that is, ſaid you, <hi>Sate in darkneſſe, and shaddow of death,</hi> deſtitute of all means of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, by hearing the Goſpell, whereto you added; <hi>But you are not ſo dead, for as much as you live under Goſpell light.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As touching which, to me as yet, the main or intire deſign of the Apoſtle in that <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. to <hi>verſe</hi> 9. is to prove that more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, which he had avouched, in <hi>chap.</hi> 1. <hi>verſe</hi> 19. in generall; namely, that we beleeve through the working of that very excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding great power, which raiſed Chriſt from the dead, which he demonſtrates from the difficulty of the work of faith; not at all ſhewing by what outward meanes that power wrought, or by what inſtrument but the great difficulty of the work, in that 'tis no leſſe than a quickning from the dead, parallell to Chriſts, which nothing but an Almighty power could effect; and whether they had the Goſpell preached along ſpace to them, or the contrary, that makes nothing to his purpoſe, for they were quickned by the Goſpell, as a means uſed, and whether God doth it at firſt hearing as 3000. are conceived to be at once, or whether afterwards; ſtill tis done by the ſame Almighty power alone, improving that means (for <hi>faith comes by hearing</hi>) and that in one inſtant, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſooner or later. And that they here ſaid to be <hi>dead in ſins,</hi> were ſuch as <hi>ſate in darkeneſſe, &amp;c.</hi> ſeems very ſtrange, conſidering the perſons ſo ſaid to be dead: <hi>We were dead;</hi> Who? I <hi>Paul,</hi> and you <hi>Epheſians.</hi> Whereof concerning <hi>Paul,</hi> what more contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictory, than to ſay, <hi>Paul had not the light of the Gospell as we have,</hi> and therefore not ſo dead: concerning whom 'tis moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, from his own affirmation of what he did in point of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, that 'twas out of <hi>zeal,</hi> he followed his light, therefore he ſo long continued to hear the Goſpell, before he perſecuted it,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:121088:8"/>as according to his utmoſt power, to ſee whether it were falſ or true, and after that (ſeeing ground ſufficient, by his light to juſtifie, yea to require his zealous perſecution thereof) for a long time, he was ingaged in a way of perſecution, bearing the Office of a Promooter or Informer, <hi>carrying letters, &amp;c. to the chief Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells,</hi> and how pragmaticall he was in that deſigne, might be proved at large from <hi>Acts</hi> 7. the end, and <hi>Acts</hi> 8. <hi>verſe</hi> 1.2. He muſt then needs live in the time of the Goſpell (when he might have had means of grace, but rejected it all the time wherein he perſecuted the Goſpell: he could not perſecute the Goſpell in a time wherein the Goſpell was not preached, or profeſſed: he would not fight with his own ſhaddow; Therefore he <hi>ſate not in the shaddow of death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yea, it ſeemes eaſie to prove, he had the Goſpell a long time before, and that upon record, which was in great requeſt with him, being written in the Prophets, which he ſearched; and that in them he read Goſpell, is clear from <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.17. <hi>For therein,</hi> In what? In the Goſpell of Chriſt, <hi>is revealed faith, &amp;c.</hi> How proves he this? It follows, <hi>as 'tis written;</hi> What's written ſhall teſtifie to what he aſſerts, and 'tis written, <hi>The just shall live by faith:</hi> Where written? In the New Teſtament? No, that was not written when he ſpake this; Where then? In the Goſpell preached by <hi>Habbacuck chap.</hi> 2. <hi>ver.</hi> 4. So this <hi>Paul</hi> affirms, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.11. The Scripture ſaith, <hi>who beleeves on him, even Ieſus Chriſt, shall not be ashamed; namely, notwithſtanding all oppoſers, even by vertue of his juſtification:</hi> and where doth the Scripture ſay thus, which is the ſum of the Goſpell, even in <hi>Eſay</hi> 28.11.</p>
               <p>As touching the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> in what ſence <hi>Paul</hi> was dead, ſo were they; <hi>We who were dead,</hi> he makes his own and their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition joyntly one; and that the <hi>Epheſians</hi> diſtinctly conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>ſate not in darkneſſe,</hi> ſeemes hence, in that he directed that Epiſtle <hi>To the Saints at Epheſus,</hi> as being a place, where men pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt the Goſpell, and therefore lived under it.</p>
               <p>But hence, to proceede to the fifth particular, next enſuing the former, to this effect.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Men that are ſo dead in ſins, &amp;c. have a naturall life, of reaſon, Iudgement, underſtanding, conſcience, &amp;c. by vertue whereof men are able to weigh and ponder ſuch wayes or means tendred to them, yea ſuch a power they have in them, as whereby (if they will put it
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:121088:8"/>forth, and imploy it accordingly,) they may do ſuch things, as unto which God hath by way of promiſe, annexed grace and acceptation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For which beſides the places mentioned; namely, thoſe already queſtioned, <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.37. and <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.7. you further alleadged, <hi>Prov.</hi> 2. <hi>verſe</hi> 1, 2, 3. and <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.27.</p>
               <p>Now in reference to this fifth aſſertion, I cannot but as yet utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deny naturall men, to be able ſo to improve naturall power, as to ingage God, &amp;c. according to the affertion preſcript.</p>
               <p>For which end, I ſhall firſt deny the ſame to be proved in the leaſt, by thoſe other Texts alleadged.</p>
               <p>For that in <hi>Prov.</hi> 2. <hi>verſe</hi> 1.2. &amp;c. I yet ſee no reaſon at all, why it ſhould be underſtood as ſpoken to naturall men, but good reaſon whence to conclude it ſpoken poſitively of beleevers; <hi>My Son,</hi> Whoſe ſon? Wiſedomes ſon, or the ſon of <hi>Solomon,</hi> inſpired with the ſpirit of Wiſdome, or of him rather, typiſied by <hi>Salomon</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>the wiſedome of the Father; My Son,</hi> or thou who art begotten again of Wiſedome, and my reaſon why he means not Naturall men, I deduce out of the firſt chapter: a great part whereof, even from verſe 8. to 20. is directed to beleavers, in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to Naturall men, termed ſinners, (by which term ſuch are moſt obviouſly pointed out in Scripture,) which I gather from verſe 7. where, having to the 7. <hi>verſe,</hi> ſet forth the excellent uſe of the book, <hi>To know Wiſdome &amp;c.</hi> in the 7. <hi>verſe</hi> he declares to whom they ſhall become ſo excellent, or on what terms men at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain excellency by ſtuddying this book, expreſt thus; <hi>The fear of the Lord is the beginning of knowledge, but fools, &amp;c.</hi> So that the fundamentall qualification, by virtue whereof men come to be proficients in the School of Spirituall wiſdome, is this, <hi>That they have the fear of the Lord;</hi> thats the beginning of all ſaving know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, the very firſt leſſon, firſt of all to be learned, as funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall.</p>
               <p>But ſhall not naturall men upon improving naturall abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, attain ſound knowledge? No, all beſides ſuch as have the ground-work of all layd in them, even the fear of the Lord, are excluded ſo long from all ſpirituall and ſaving know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, as in the terme enſuing, <hi>But fools despiſe, &amp;c.</hi> Who are thoſe fools? all without exception, that have not this fear; How is that proved? Becauſe that's the very beginning of knowledge; Therefore ſo long as they are not as yet <hi>Ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>darians,</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:121088:9"/>having not the beginning of knowledge, they muſt needs be fools; and that by fools is meant, All that have not the Lords fear in them, and therefore muſt be a note of excluſion to all that have not this fear, ſeemes clear, becauſe all are comprehended in theſe two, ſuch as have feare, and fools; and no medium between. According to which double poſition laid down in <hi>verſ.</hi> 7. ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing who they were that learned wiſdome by theſe Proverbs, and and who not: He directs his Exhortation to him that could learn Wiſdome; namely, who is poſſeſt with this fear, and that moſt peculiarly, by way of excluding it from all others: <hi>My Son, if ſinnes, verſe</hi> 10. Again, <hi>verſe</hi> 15. <hi>My Son walk not thou in the way with them,</hi> ſo that the holy Ghoſt, that Spirit of Wiſdome, makes a mighty difference between him that is his Son, as one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten a new by him; who hath Gods fear, and all others not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object </seg>
                  </label> But cannot all others attain Spirituall knowledge as well as he, by exact improving naturall abilities? No, for thereby they cannot purchaſe the ground-work, <hi>The fear of the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw </seg>
                  </label> But yet in the 22. and 23. <hi>verſes,</hi> ſhe directs her voyce in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall to all in <hi>the ſtrees, ſimple ones, ſcorners, and fools hating know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, &amp;c.</hi> That they would turn from their folly by Wiſdomes reproofs, may not ſuch qualifie themſelves by their naturall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provements, that they may aſſuredly attain ſaving Wiſedome, or turn from their folly at Wiſdomes reproofs? No, for in <hi>verſe</hi> 23. having in the firſt part of it commanded, <hi>Fools, Turn ye at my reproof:</hi> to prevent an Objection, How ſhall we turn? The holy Ghoſt declares how this work is wrought, undertaking it himſelf; Behold, or take notice how this great overture is brought about, even thus: <hi>Ile poure out my Spirit to you, Ile make known my words to you:</hi> Firſt, <hi>pour out my Spirit,</hi> whereby poſſeſſing you with the fear of the Lord, and ſo will <hi>make known, &amp;c.</hi> after; laying firſt the foundation of all ſaving knowledge.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object </seg>
                  </label> But how appeares it that their improving Naturalls did not render them capable by ingaging God, &amp;c. even of ſaving know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw </seg>
                  </label> Even thus, beſides whats before, becauſe thoſe whom wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome undertakes to give ſaving knowledge to, were no otherwiſe qualified, than the worſt of them, againſt whom he reſolvedly proteſts, never to give ſaving knowledge to: <hi>Behold, Ile pour out
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:121088:9"/>my ſpirit to you;</hi> to whom? you who have improved your natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall abilities, ſo as to ingage me? No: to whom then? <hi>To you ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ones that love ſimplicity, ſcorners delighting in ſcorning,</hi> and to <hi>you fools hating knowledge;</hi> by which we may judge whether they qualified themſelves, or ingaged God by Naturall improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: How is the work done then? even by the Spirits over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powring of ſuch thats the onely ground of the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween perſons in themſelves alike qualified; and therefore no precedent improvement, though ever ſo tranſcendent, for the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſort from whom the Spirit will for ever with hold the ſaving operation, are expreſt to have the ſelfe-ſame qualifications, <hi>to hate knowledge, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Or if by <hi>Son</hi> you mean men improving their naturall abilities, as that to them the promiſe is certainly made, it ſhall be granted you, that be he what he will, Whoſoever askes as is there requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, he ſhall have his deſire granted; but it follows not therefore that naturall men can ſo aske: The thing promiſed on asking you acknowledge to import acceptation with God: but ſhall it be had upon every asking? No, Tis Wiſdome whereof <hi>James</hi> tells us in the place fore-named, in expreſſe termes, it cannot be had but upon asking in faith; ſo that whoſoever be meant by <hi>Son</hi> here, he muſt aske in faith; without which his naturall improvements ingage not God at all. Not but that ſuch muſt improve naturall abilities, for 'tis their duty, but yet thereupon 'tis not Gods duty to confer Grace.</p>
               <p>Again, for I decline exact method, as not becoming me; the manner after which this duty is to be done, appears expreſly to be with greateſt attention and intention; <hi>Apply thy heart &amp;c. If thou cryeſt after, lifteſt up thy voyce, ſeekeſt her as ſilver, &amp;c.</hi> Now according to that known ſaying, <hi>Ignoti nulla cupido,</hi> 'tis impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble meer naturall men, not poſſeſt with the fear of God, which is the very beginning of all ſaving knowledge; ſhould be able ſo to <hi>apply their hearts, cry after it, ſeek &amp;c.</hi> Taking pains as one digging in a mine for hid Treaſures: ſwine are not wont to take ſuch paines for pearls. As yet therefore I cannot conceive this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation to be chiefely directed to naturall men, as having a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſo to perform the duty, as to ingage God to inſtate them in the promiſe, which to prove you bring it, but in ſtrictneſſe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety, as 'tis a promiſe 'tis onely abſolutely given to them that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:121088:10"/>have faith, though the condition on our part ſo concerns naturall men, as to inform them what their duty is, as all other of Gods Commands do, with making known of which, God is not bound to inable all that know their duty to do it; ſo that while naturall, 'tis impoſſible for them to keep any one ſavingly.</p>
               <p>The next Text alledged is, <hi>John</hi> 6.27. <hi>Labour, &amp;c. For that meat which endures to eternall life, which the ſon of man ſhall give to you;</hi> namely, (ſaid you) Upon labouring, even Naturall mens Labouring, to whom you direct the exhortation, and that to prove the fifth aſſertion preſcribed, to which refer; ſo that by <hi>Labour</hi> you underſtand a mans improving his Naturalls with greateſt diligence; on which, God according to his promiſe will give everlaſting meat, or ſaving Grace, whereby to intereſt them into Chriſt, who is life everlaſting. But that by <hi>Labouring</hi> here Chriſt means not their own full improvement of Naturall abilities, only or chiefely, as whereunto annexing a promiſe ſeemes evident; becauſe by <hi>Labouring</hi> he means true beleeving, which I prove from 28. and 29. <hi>verſes,</hi> Chriſt having exhorted them to <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, &amp;c.</hi> Thereupon they perceiving the Exhortation to import <hi>Everlasting life,</hi> were inquiſitive in verſe 28. <hi>What ſhall we do, that we might ſo labour,</hi> for the word for <hi>Labour</hi> in the 27. <hi>verſ.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and that in 28. <hi>verſe</hi> following <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, tranſlated <hi>might work,</hi> are the ſame, ſo that their queſtion propounded was in reference to the duty injoyned before, that they might under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the nature of that Command, whereto Chriſt anſwers, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them what <hi>labour</hi> or work 'twas he required of them; where the word tranſlated work <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, anſwers the <hi>Verb,</hi> whence alſo the <hi>Verb</hi> is derived, and ſo joyntly import <hi>Labour</hi> in all three <hi>verſes,</hi> which work then is to beleeve in Jeſus Chriſt, as is direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly laid down in expreſſe termes, <hi>verſe</hi> 29. If then <hi>labouring</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports the ſaving work of beleeving, then 'tis more then utmoſt improvement of Naturalls, becauſe by ſuch improvement, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not work the great work of faith: ſo then by <hi>Labour</hi> he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands more then Naturall improvement. And becauſe 'tis a work far above the reach of mans Naturall improvements, he that giv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s it in command undertakes to work his own will, or command in them, which follows, <hi>Which the Son of man ſhall give unto you.</hi> So as 'tis here granted, Chriſt requires them to improve their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall abilities, but yet withall, that alſo which is infinitely above
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:121088:10"/>them all, how fully ſoever improved, even ſaving faith, <hi>Which the Son of man ſhall give,</hi> they muſt impove, &amp;c. but yet after all, muſt reſt in nothing but Chriſts gift, they were ſo to labour by naturall improvement, as to ſubmit to, or rather cloſe with the Spirits ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding great inſpiring power, whereby it works faith.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object </seg>
                  </label> But could they not ſo labour by naturall improvement, as to ingage Chriſt to give them everlaſting meat, certainly upon their labouring, which 'tis brought to prove?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw </seg>
                  </label> For Anſwer, as yet I conceive, that they had no promiſe made on their meer <hi>Labour,</hi> though to utmoſt improving naturall abilities, which I prove thus clearly, becauſe they did <hi>labour</hi> according to their power, for they took as good a courſe as naturall reaſon could preſcribe: Firſt, they deſired to underſtand what their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty expreſt by the tearm <hi>Labour</hi> did import; next they deſired in a moſt rationall way, ſome good ground whereon to ſtabliſh, or bottome this their duty of beleeving even by ſome ſign, which was an ancient manner of confirming great matters, in anſwere whereto he declares himſelf to be the true ſigne from heaven, the bread of God; whereupon according to the ſtrength of naturall underſtanding imprinting in them a deſire of happineſſe, becauſe 'tis again, and again affirmed to be the bread of life, they put forth the utmoſt of their Naturall abilities in this great requeſt; <hi>Lord ever more give us this Bread,</hi> whence Chriſt again declares himſelfe to be that Bread, and further tells them who ſhould par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take thereof, <hi>even he that comes to me, or beleeves in me,</hi> (not eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry comming, for theſe came, yet to them he ſaith, <hi>ye beleeve not</hi>) <hi>ſhall never hunger, &amp;c.</hi> whereby alluring them to come, and yet after their improvement of naturall abilities in affectionate as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings, Chriſt tells them, <hi>Ye come not</hi> ſo, as <hi>to have life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But is not their not improving Naturalls given as the reaſon thereof? <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object </seg>
                  </label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw </seg>
                  </label> No, in no wiſe, for they improved their Reaſon, judgement, &amp;c. to the utmoſt; yet further, to finde out how it ſhould be true, That Chriſt was the bread of heaven, and that by inquiry into his ſtem, or Parentage whence he was; the beſt courſe their natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall light could guide them to, which they followed in <hi>verſe</hi> 41. and 42. but doth Chriſt hereupon tell them; Ye have not yet ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly improved your naturalls, therefore 'tis you beleeve not? or doth he expreſſe by way of promiſe, that becauſe you have impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:121088:11"/>&amp;c. in reaſoning, diſputing, begging, &amp;c. Therefore according to my ſure promiſe, ingaging me, Ile ſecond your improvement with grace, I will give it you? No, but contrarily, the reaſon why they cannot come to life, or beleeve, which he had ſaid in <hi>verſe</hi> 36. he gives them in <hi>verſe</hi> 44. <hi>No man can,</hi> or hath power to <hi>come, Except the Father draw him,</hi> which act he was not inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to put forth on them, notwithſtanding their moſt rationall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provements; <hi>Except the Father draw him,</hi> not except he draws, or ſurely ingages the Father by improvements, but there will be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of further inlargements on this from what follows; we ſee here, that inſteed of being ingaged by promiſe by naturall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provements, we have the contrary; he ſaith not becauſe you have imployed Naturalls, therefore according to my promiſe, I will ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cond it with grace, but contrarily notwithſtanding your utmoſt improvements; Yet <hi>No man</hi> (be he ever ſo accurate in naturall improvements) <hi>can come, except the Father draw him,</hi> which to do, no improvements can draw God.</p>
               <p>You next alleadged another Scripture, <hi>Luke</hi> 13.24. <hi>Strive to enter in;</hi> but as touching this I finde no abſolute promiſe of Grace annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, from Gods being ingaged by naturall improvements, therefore not as yet ſeeing any thing conſiderable therein, whereof to take notice, ſhall ſtep over to what appeares to be of greater moment.</p>
               <p>Wherein, though I conceive it ſufficient to have depoſed what I conceive, againſt the proofs whereon you ground your fifth aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion, yet I ſhall with great preſumption on your patience, and candid conſtruction, give my grounds for the contrary; namely, to prove that Naturall men, <hi>dead, &amp;c.</hi> have not ſuch a power of Reaſon, Judgement, &amp;c. as whereby if they will accordingly put it forth, they may do ſuch things, as whereunto God hath by promiſe annexed Grace, which I conceive might be clearly made out from ſundry Scriptures, whereof to Name, 2. or 3.</p>
               <p>One is, <hi>Iohn.</hi> 5. <hi>verſe</hi> 39. <hi>Search the Scriptures,</hi> concerning which, though the firſt word be uſually rendered, as the Impera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Mood, <hi>Search ye</hi> as a Command given to ſearch, yet for my part, as yet (with Submiſſion to the judicious) I finde not, how it may be read with good ſence any other way, then as the Indicative Mood, <hi>ye do ſearch;</hi> which I ground not onely on my own Judgement (though I finde this that the Originall Word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Scrutamini,</hi> may as properly be ſo rendered) for as
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:121088:11"/>I remember, 'tis the Judgement of Doctor <hi>Homes,</hi> as in his book <hi>Of new Heavens and new Earth,</hi> I have ſeen, though not ſince divers moneths by-gone: and that it may moſt properly be thus rendred, may (as I conceive) be moſt cleerly proved from the context: the occaſion of all Chriſts diſcourſe, from the 19. <hi>verſe</hi> of that 5. <hi>chap.</hi> ſeemes chiefely to ariſe, from whats expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in <hi>verſe</hi> 18. where this is given as one reaſon, why they <hi>ſought to kill Christ, becauſe he had ſaid, God was his Father, making himſelf equall with God, &amp;c.</hi> Whereupon Chriſt all along for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, in a moſt convincing manner, proves the truth of that for which the Jews would needs have ſlain him, to which purpoſe telling them, God ſent not Chriſt onely to bear witneſſe of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, but ſent his fore-runner <hi>John,</hi> to bear witneſſe, which <hi>John ye ſent to</hi> your ſelves, <hi>verſe</hi> 33. who accordingly <hi>bave witneſſe</hi> of me; and he was once a man in great credit with you, therefore why might not his Teſtimony carry it? Yea, after he had named other grounds of teſtimony from his Works done, and the Fathers own Teſtimony that ſent him, he adds yet a further ground of confirmation in this 39. <hi>verſe,</hi> even from their own practiſe, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, in ſending to know <hi>Johns</hi> judgement; ſo here, from their own diligent inquiry into the Scriptures, <hi>ye do ſearch,</hi> even your ſelves do; <hi>the ſcriptures,</hi> namely the writings of the Prophets which alone were then written, as of <hi>Moſes</hi> particularly inſiſted on.</p>
               <p>Again, that they did ſearch them is clear from what follows, <hi>Moſes</hi> ſhall accuſe you, <hi>verſe</hi> 45. whoſe Accuſation ſhall be a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient witneſſe againſt them without Chriſts: Why? Becauſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y peruſed his writings, and ſo were rendred inexcuſeable: yea further cleer from the concluding clauſe of that 45. <hi>verſe, In whom,</hi> (viz. Moſes) <hi>ye trust,</hi> or, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>in whom ye hope:</hi> now had they not ſearched diligently, and conformed to his wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, they would not have built ſuch hope thereon; knowledge muſt precede confidence. Which acception ſuppoſed to be moſt warrantable, ſeemes conſiderable towards the proof of whats affirmed. <hi>Ye ſearch</hi> which word imports exact and accurate ſcrutiny, and no marvail, for therefore <hi>ye ſearch,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>becauſe in them, ye think to have eternall life,</hi> upon this very ground they ſearched, and therefore with all their utmoſt care and diligence, as conceiving to finde life in them; which <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf, that ſtrict Phariſee <hi>ſearched</hi> ſo into, as that he thought, he had found
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:121088:12"/>
                  <hi>life</hi> in them, but yet was <hi>dead,</hi> whiles ſo <hi>alive, Rom.</hi> 7, 8, 9. <hi>and they are they that teſtifie of me,</hi> thoſe Scriptures which ye think to have life by from the letter of them, teſtifie of me: what? it muſt have reference (as I conceive) to what they ſought for: namely, eternall life, they teſtifie then that what life ye think to have in them, muſt be had in me, they ſend you from themſelves to the Meſſia, pointed at by them, as <hi>John</hi> ſent ſuch as he baptized with water, to Chriſt, to be baptized with the Holy Ghoſt. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding your ſearching, <hi>ye will not come to me that ye might have life,</hi> which proves that mens naturall improvements do not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage God to give them ſaving faith, without which, through utmoſt improvements they could only look on the Scripture while pointing to a Meſſia, but as a covenant of works and learned by all, but to be ſelfe Juſticiaries; which ſanctuary of juſtification by works we moſt obviouſly finde was the ſtrongeſt one, which the profoundeſt wiſdome of the Jewes could erect, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.8.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object </seg>
                  </label> But it may be objected, Chriſt in <hi>Verſe</hi> 40. charges them with this, <hi>Ye will not come to have life,</hi> or in faith; doth it not hence ſeem that they might have power to believe or to ingage God to to give faith, which power they did not put forth as they might; and that's the reaſon why ye believe not?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw </seg>
                  </label> Whereto for anſwer, for the former ſuppoſition, that they might have power to believe, that you abſolutely conclude againſt. For the latter, which you avouch, that they might ſo ingage them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in improvements as to ingage God to give faith, this muſt as yet be denied, becauſe here they did improve to their utmoſt their naturals in ſearching, even as for life, and yet God added not faith, which is moſt undeniably proved in <hi>Chap.</hi> 6. from <hi>Verſe</hi> 28 to 45. Wherein, the whole diſcourſe moſt inevitably demonſtrates that they did as it were put all their naturall powers of reaſon, judgement, &amp;c. on the wrack, as is before ſhewed by propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing queſtions, rationall diſcuſſing them, praying for, &amp;c. But all this did not make Chriſt confeſſe, I ſee you have done your utmoſt, therefore Ile perform mine engagements to give ſaving faith: no, he tearms their ſtrongeſt reaſonings but <hi>murmurings,</hi> adding no promiſe thereunto, and therefore not ingaged thereby ſo to do; and conſequently their not improving naturals is not the reaſon of Gods not giving faith, which I prove plainly from <hi>Chap.</hi> 6. <hi>Verſe</hi> 44. where after he had ſaid in <hi>Chap.</hi> 40. <hi>ye will not come,</hi> that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:121088:12"/>is in faith, being to life, and repeated it more plainly in <hi>Chap.</hi> 6. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſe</hi> 36. ye believe not, after their great reaſoning on the matter, Chriſt tells them the reaſon of their not believing, to put an end to their murmurings and diſputings, <hi>murmure not, &amp;c.</hi> think not ſo to prevaile by your reaſonings, as if God were bound thereon to give you ſaving knowledge, or thereby ſurely to attaine faith: why ſo? 'tis added <hi>Verſe</hi> 44. becauſe Gods free diſpenſation is the great reaſon, <hi>No man can come to me except the Father draw him:</hi> not, <hi>ye cannot come becauſe of not improving naturals.</hi> Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding which, ye come not, becauſe the father muſt draw, before ye can come ſavingly, which God is not bound to do by vertue of your improvements, ſtill continuing a free agent in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſing grace. <hi>No man can come, &amp;c.</hi> No man whoſoever, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which indefinite tearm he comprehends all howſoever quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, or improved, concluding the ground of all mens being not able, or not having power to come to God, to be Gods not draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them: Gods ſuſpending grace, which he may do from whom he pleaſes, is given as the ground of the defect of faith in every man whomſoever that wants it, therefore not the want of naturall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provements, he tells them, <hi>no man can come,</hi> by which tearme of excluſion he debars all without exception, that are not drawne, that ſo theſe that were moſt inquiſitive according to naturall light, might not wonder at their exemption, though they had proceeded in a probable way, and courſe in order thereto. Non-improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment cannot (as I conceive) be a true ground of not believing, becauſe utmoſt improvement cannot procure believing, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is no true, or certain ground, or reaſon of our believing, which you make it (as I conceive) and that by making it to engage God to give faith; whereas the Fathers not drawing is given as the onely reaſon of it, and not a want of being ingaged by us: Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans and Sinners were as capable of faith as the learned Scribes, and did as much ingage God, though it be commendable for natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall men to do their utmoſt, yea, and moſt hopefull, for as much as they are in Gods way.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object </seg>
                  </label> Another proof is, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.7. <hi>Iſrael hath not obtained grace,</hi> but did he ſeek for't? yes, for 'tis ſaid, what Iſrael ſought for he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained not: did he not, what God required in order thereto?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw </seg>
                  </label> For anſwer, what God requires, <hi>Math.</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 7. fore toucht on, <hi>Seek, &amp;c.</hi> that Iſrael is ſaid to have done here, in reſpect of the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:121088:13"/>outward performance as naturall men; the command, <hi>Seek,</hi> in <hi>Matthew</hi> is of the ſimple Verbe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the duty here acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to be done by them, is of the compounded Verbe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>requiro,</hi> as if they had ſought with ſuch earneſtneſſe and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, as one <hi>requiring</hi> or commanding, which they might juſtly have commanded, if by their ſeeking they could ingage God to accept them, as according to a promiſe made; for God by the law of his faithfulneſſe is bound to performe the law of his promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. Yes, the word here being the compound Verbe ſeems to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, if it might be, greater inteation in ſeeking then that in <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew,</hi> therefore elſewhere tranſlated <hi>expeto,</hi> as <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.39. it appears' then they ſought with utmoſt intention, according to na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall power: but whence is it they fail'd of their end? we ſhall finde the ground of the difference evidently to be Gods free di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſation, and that from a double demonſtration from the ground given, why others obtained grace, <hi>but the election hath obtained;</hi> what's the reaſon why ſome above others, ſeeing all are ſaid to have ſought for't, even by virtue of their <hi>election?</hi> which is put in oppoſition to ſuch as attained not, though carefull ſeekers alike, ſhewing, tis not ſeeking (for he was found of them that ſought him not) but Gods free election, that diverſified their conditions in reſpect of grace, who in reſpect of naturall endeavours, ſought one as well as another.</p>
               <p>But what's the reaſon the non-election obtained not? 'tis ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <hi>the reſt were blinded:</hi> how blinded? thats ſhewed by rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, a ſore judgement of ſpirituall blindneſſe which God poured on them, denounced in <hi>Eſay</hi> 29.10. <hi>God hath given them the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of ſlumber, eyes that they ſhould not ſee, &amp;c.</hi> or God hath ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended the ſaving diſcovery of faith, without which they have onely their own naturall wiſdome to improve, which is but as eyes, that cannot ſee, we finde no other ground given for the clearing of the matter: which place now alleadged being ſo plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pertinent for expedition ſake, I ſhall commend to your conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration for a more rationall and methodicall concluding thence, what's proved thereby, eſpecially, as it may moſt aptly be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in oppoſition to what was aſſerted from <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.7. for as much as we here ſee, there's a ſeeking which ſhall never finde. But declining this, ſhall proceed to another proof; wherefore I might as I conceive as fitly alleadge that in <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.25. Chriſt
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:121088:13"/>bleſſes the <hi>Father, for that he hid from the wiſe and prudent,</hi> what was <hi>revealed to babes:</hi> what's the reaſon? is it becauſe the prudent were leſſe able, or diligent? no, that were ſtrange; but the reaſon is added, <hi>even ſo Father.</hi> Why is it ſo? <hi>for it ſeemed good in thy ſight:</hi> or thus; becauſe it pleaſed thee, 'twas the good pleaſure of his will; who ſuſpending grace from men moſt probably capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the eye of reaſon, diſpended it to <hi>Babes,</hi> which were in no probable way of attaining it, thereby to honour his own freedome; nothing is ſaid to make the difference between each party but Gods revealing, and that with infinite perfection of freedome, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe 'twas agreeable to the good pleaſure of his will.</p>
               <p>Againe, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.10. ſaid the Diſciples, <hi>Why speakeſt thou to them in parables? i.e.</hi> to the Jewes: Chriſt anſwers, <hi>Becauſe, to you is given to know the myſteries, and not to them.</hi> Chriſt uttered himſelf in a dark myſticall way to them; becauſe, God who is a free giver of free-grace ſuſpended the gift of his grace, whereby to magnifie his freedome; and he ſhewes, he doth this in anſwer to the prophecy of <hi>Eſay</hi> 6.9.10. where 'tis, <hi>Goe tell them, heare ye indeed, and underſtand not, &amp;c. make their hearts fat, and their eares heavie, &amp;c.</hi> According whereto he ſpeaks here myſtically, leaving them to their own naturall blindneſſe; ſo that it ſeemes clear, the ground of the difference was from Gods free diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ye underſtand they not; becauſe to you, is given, to them not.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object </seg>
                  </label> But it may be objected, did not the Diſciples improve their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turals with greater dexterity then the Jewes, ſo as to engage God, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw </seg>
                  </label> For anſwer, Chriſt gives this as a full and pertinent anſwer to the queſtion propounded, by which anſwer he reſolves all, into the free grace of God, in giving it to ſome, and not to others; and whether or not the Diſciples diverſified themſelves from the Jewes in point of ing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ging God, by improvements, let us take the example of that Apoſtle <hi>Matthew,</hi> that utters this; who was ſo farre from improving naturals, whereby to ingage Chriſt to call him, as that he was <hi>call'd ſitting at the receir of cuſtome, Mat.</hi> 9.9. Which as is generally concluded, was a very injurious oppreſſing office, or ſervice; and as touching him ſelf a generall, he was a Publican, and ſuch we moſt obviouſly finde in Scripture ranked with ſinners, as the moſt nefarious and profane; ſo far ſhort of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:121088:14"/>the Phariſees in point of naturall improvements, as that they coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it unlawfull for Chriſt to eat with perſons ſo vile, ſo <hi>Matth.</hi> 9.11. 'Tis clear then, that in <hi>Matthew</hi> it muſt needs be of free gift, without reference to any ingagement, upon his improvement; and if ſo, then whatſoever was the reaſon, why grace was given to <hi>Matthew,</hi> from the ſame ground or reaſon tis given to all the reſt; for there Chriſt gives one reaſon, for, and concerning, all the Diſciples at once; which reaſon being double, hath no reſpect to ought done by them, to whom 'tis given, as wherby to be engaged, no nor induced: not to ought undone by them, to whom 'tis not given.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object </seg>
                  </label> But it may be objected, from that of <hi>Matthew.</hi> 13. <hi>verſ.</hi> 12. <hi>Whoſoever hath, &amp;c.</hi> This ſeems to have relation to ſome thing in the perſons, but in reference to this, as likewiſe the next forego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and what may be objected againſt each, I ſhall not in the leaſt attempt ought now; becauſe, as I remember, the maine of what may be objected againſt them, may be collected out of your laſt Expoſition-exerciſe ſave one; concerning which, as likewiſe the laſt of all, I cannot but as yet much diſſent from; though ſince that, have had no opportunity of peruſall at all, though upon near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I could not but immediately purpoſe by your ſavour humbly to crave ſome ſatisfaction, which now ſhall totally decline, yea, and yet for ſome ſeaſon.</p>
               <p>Yet another proof, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.1, 2, 3. <hi>Paul</hi> there utters himſelf in <hi>Iſraels</hi> behalf, as having his bowels <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ouled within him, for them; expreſſing his pitifull deſires, &amp;c. for their <hi>ſalvation:</hi> and what's the reaſon, he is ſo exceeding deſirous of their good? it immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately followes, <hi>for I bear them record, &amp;c.</hi> But why is he ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident of <hi>their zeal</hi> as to atteſt it ſo peremptorily? Doubtleſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he knew it in himſelf before converſion, as he affirmes. And why not according to knowledge? <hi>for they were ignorant of Gods righteouſneſſe,</hi> which is <hi>of faith:</hi> he here ſolemnly teſtifies in the behalf of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in generall, <hi>they had a zeale of God;</hi> which muſt import moſt ardent affection in them, according to their power: but were they not ſparing of their labour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> were they in earneſt? Yea doubtleſſe, zeal muſt import great ardency, as far as their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall knowledge could carry them, but not according to uſe knowledge: all their fault was, they had not ſaving knowledge,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:121088:14"/>which is all he charges them with, after he had atteſted them, <hi>to have a zeal of God,</hi> or thoſe zealous endeavours after righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, which God required; only th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> wanted the ſaving eye of faith, to guide their zeal, for they did endeavour alſo; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore 'tis ſaid, <hi>going about to ſtabliſh, &amp;c.</hi> They went about it, or ſetled to it as their work. And this was the ground of his <hi>hearts deſire and prayer to God</hi> (who had already pardoned <hi>Pauls</hi> miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guided zeal, in perſecuting the Church) for them, as putting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in Gods ordinary way; yet in the end of the Chapter, he ſhewes, moſt of them miſcarried, the reaſon whereof, the 8 <hi>Verſe</hi> of the ſucceeding Chapter ſhewes, was Gods ſuſpending grace, as 'tis dilated on before.</p>
               <p>How undeniably might it be proved by the example of <hi>Paul,</hi> if time would permit, who paralell to us, had the Goſpell preached as well as written in the Prophets, to improve, how rationall a man was he, how ſtrict in ſtudying and conforming himſelf to the writings of the Prophets, the rule of life preſcribed? ſo exact therein, as that he affirmes himſelf <hi>as touching the righteouſneſſe, which was by the Law blameleſſe,</hi> ſo that he was able to juſtifie himſelf, after his moſt rationall and diligent ſearching the Law, and inviolable obſerving thereof, concluding himſelf to be <hi>alive to the law</hi> in the letter, in reſpect of his own naturall judgement and account, he could learn no better leſſon thence, till the ſpirit of the Law, or by the law, ſlew him.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object </seg>
                  </label> But did not this his accurateneſſe ingage God to give him ſaving faith?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw </seg>
                  </label> No, for the contrary is moſt evident; for after he had to his ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt improved himſelf, God gave him up to that horrible ſinne of perſecution of the Church, for a great ſpace, as is before ſhewed: which ſhould never have been done, had he been rightly qualified for faith by naturall improvements: God ſuſpends not grace from ſubjects meetly prepared for it; nor could God have ſuſpended grace from him, had he by his naturall improvements ingaged God to give him grace thereupon: nay, is it not moſt manifeſt, as touching all his naturall improvements, that by how much the more tranſcendent they were, they ſet him at a greater diſtance from any capableneſſe of ſaving grace, being ſo confirmed and confident in his own righteouſneſſe ſo much the more, and ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſing
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:121088:15"/>the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt; and therefore God ſmote him in ſuch a wonderfull manner in order to his conviction: and if <hi>Pauls</hi> improvement could not ingage God to adde grace, which is moſt undeniable, then neither ſhall any mans elſe, while the world ſtands: for as much as <hi>Paul</hi> was as arch an improver as can be imagined, which might be abundantly confirmed, but ſhall not dare; ſpecially, becauſe it would be but a ſuperfluous labour in a thing ſo obvious; nor yet to enlarge further on this argument at preſent, though much might be, as I conceive, needfully added, to ſignifie the dangerous conſeqeunces inevitably deduceable from theſe aſſertions, which ſeem much to abridge or confine free grace, as diſpenſed on more free tearms to ſome, then to others: as alſo the poyſon which Formaliſts may ſuck out of this, who having improved their naturals (as who not in ſuch time of great know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and countenancing of Religion?) may conclude they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, becauſe God is bound thereon to adde it, and will performe his engagements; but I ſhall at preſent onely inſert this following opinion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Facienti quod in ſe eſt, in viribus naturalibus, Deus tenetur dare gratiam ſufficientem adſalutem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which, and that not long ſince was expreſt by an able Divine, to be a main maxime of the <hi>Arminians,</hi> and how to diſtinguiſh between the importance of your fifth aſſertion, and this ſentence, I muſt profeſſe I am utterly unable.</p>
               <p>But afterwards you gave a diſtinction by way of caution: namely, that it followes not, that men have a power in them without Gods aſſiſtance to believe. Wherefore you added, they have a power, but not a diſpoſition, and that we muſt diſtinguiſh between having a power and an inclination; to which, I at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſay one word: he that hath not a will, hath not a power, and ſo wants an executive power; by which I conceive you mean a power whereby to execute, which you affirme a naturall man hath. That ſuch want a power, I prove from <hi>John</hi> 6. <hi>verſe</hi> 44. and 65. where 'tis expreſt that a meer naturall man, without the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers drawing <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>non poteſt,</hi> hath not power; to do what? to come to life, or in faith: ſo that 'tis clear, as I conceive, that ſuch want a <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a power whereby to execute, for he that hath not power to will, hath not power to do, therefore God being
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:121088:15"/>ſaid to do all in us, is ſaid to work in us both to <hi>will</hi> and to <hi>do</hi> of his good pleaſure, 2 <hi>Phil.</hi> 13. as if the willing an act were the all in all, requiſite to produce an act<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which want of power in man you contradicted, in affirming, <hi>All that was wanting in the Jewes, or the reaſon of their not believing is placed in their will, ye will not come, he ſaith not, ye have no power, ye cannot come,</hi> which <hi>cannot come</hi> is expreſly affirmed twice in <hi>John</hi> 6.44. &amp; 65. But I muſt moſt abruptly deſiſt further enlargement as yet, praying the LORD to proſper it for the end intended, even the propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gating of truth.</p>
               <p>Whereto yet to adde one word; if in any particular here mentioned, any aſſertion of yours may ſuffer, blame not me, but your ſelf; of whom I may juſtly ſay, if any ſuch cauſe may be found for it. <hi>Tu te ipſum, tuis ipſis armis visiſti,</hi> for that God hath communicated much of my ſtrength, by the way of your Miniſtery.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="sermon">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:121088:16"/>
               <head>A Sermon, in Anſwer to the foregoing Letter, preached by Mr. J. G. April 28. 1644. taken after him exactly in Characters by M. THO. RUDYARD, a Member of his Church, and by him read over to SAMUEL LANE to Copy out, whoſe Copy exactly followes.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E deſire to look back a litttle to one paſſage that was delivered the laſt day, for the ſatisfaction of ſome, who it ſeems did not clearly underſtand it: the tenour of the motive whereby we perſwaded and preſt on men not truly converted to God, to ſeek for the grace of God, was this; That if they would give out themſelves in good earneſt in the ſearch, and ſeek for it with all their hearts, they ſhould finde it, having a while in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted on the amplification and inforcement of this motive and cleared the difficulty, how and in what ſenſe God may be ſaid to love or be gracious to men before believing, and in what not; we came to ponder the motive, wherein we put this to conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, of how great concernment 'twas to them to have fellowſhip with the Saints of God in the great buſineſſe of ſalvation, giving them aſſurance, that whatſoever their ſinnes had been, and how great ſoever their preſent guilt may be; yet, if they were but truly willing to come under the wing of Chriſt, not a haire of their heads ſhould fall to the ground. In proſecution whereof, we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded and anſwered this Objection.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object </seg>
                  </label> You put us in minde and hope of finding grace with God, if we will make our endeavours to obtaine it, but we have little en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement, for we are dead in ſins, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw </seg>
                  </label> Which we anſwered by a gradation of five ſteps. The fifth was, That though men be dead in ſins, in ſuch a ſenſe as was formerly explained, yet men have a light of reaſon, judgement, &amp;c. by
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:121088:16"/>means whereof, they are able to conſider of tearms and means pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, &amp;c. though happily not able fully to comprehend them, as to debate, whether faith in Chriſt, or the works of the Law, or their own righteouſneſs, be likely to carry it in Gods ſight, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they may not be able to come to any certain iſſue, to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the difference between each, and to reſolve in themſelves, this is the means that will do it, and that not; or ſuppoſe they finde no ſatisfaction in way of reaſon in either of thoſe means, yet are able to work it on in a way of reaſon, whether there be any other way beſides more likely. Now though 'tis not to be ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, that they have power to come to ſuch firme bottome, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to build without doubtings; yet they are able, and have a ſcale and ballance of reaſon and judgement, whereby to weigh one rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon againſt another, to ſee which is moſt hopefull, without all queſtion men may go thus far; and here re-inforcing the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: we declared to ſuch, that if they would be willing to do unfeinedly and impartially, what God hath appointed them in a way of nature to do; God hath promiſed ſucceſſe and acceptation in this way; and this was that paſſage by name, which it ſeems ſome could not ſo well underſtand or comprehend, fearing leſt it ſhould comply with the <hi>Arminian</hi> tenent, in point of Free-will; or that I ſhould magnifie naturall abilities above the line of excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency belonging to it. If they will but pleaſe to conſider for the clearing of the whole buſineſſe but two arguments, you will clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee that there is an abſolute neceſſity for maintaining ſuch an aſſertion for a truth, as this is; namely, that if naturall men will put forth themſelves to the utmoſt to what they are able to doe to comply with God in the Goſpell they ſhall finde an anſwerable ſucceſſe, and that there is an abſolute neceſſity to maintaine it for a truth; for otherwiſe, we ſhall expoſe the truth of God, the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of grace, the do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of free-grace, which we profeſſe to maintaine, we ſhall expoſe both the one and the other to an inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piable and unanſwerable reproach &amp; diſhonour; and ſuch indeed, as cannot be redeemed by any reaſon or diſtinction; or project one or other, that men are able to deviſe for the relief of it; for that on this 'twill follow, that the aſſertion we ſpeak of, that men putting forth themſelves according to what God hath in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bled them to do in a way of nature, that God will meet them with grace and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, if the former be clearly proved, then this will follow upon
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:121088:17"/>it, that this hath no conſiſtence with the opinion of Free-will, but doth indeed intrench on the beſt foundation that that opinion ſtands upon. We know 'twas an order Chriſt gave for men to deal between <hi>Caeſar</hi> and <hi>God, Give to Caeſar the things that are Caeſars, and to God, &amp;c.</hi> And indeed no man can give to God the things that are Gods, except he give to <hi>Caeſar</hi> the things that are <hi>Caeſars;</hi> and that becauſe this is one of Gods things, even our ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to the lawfull governour ſet over us by God, in things lawfull; and mans foot may ſooneſt ſlide here, even on a pretence of giving all to God liberally, to take away from him by far more then we give; and then we give only in conceit, and take away from him in reality: for the like order here is to be obſerved by us, in making diſtribution, between Nature Gods Handmaid, and creature, and God himſelf: We muſt give to Nature the things that are Natures, as to God the things that are Gods: and as in the other caſe, ſo here 'tis moſt true, That when men think to be moſt bountifull to God, and take away all from Nature, and caſt all on God; men may here daſh their foot, and and take away from God while thinking to give him. A man may ſo farre op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe Nature for Gods cauſe, till he leave not ſo much to Nature as to bear the charge of its own condemnation; and then if men leave not to Nature ſufficient to bring the guilt on it of its owne condemnation, then it muſt neceſſarily reflect upon God. But if we will conſider two Arguments in generall, we ſhall ſee that the aſſertion mentioned, that if men do what is in their power, &amp;c. they ſhall finde acceptation with God, muſt be maintained. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider this reaſon, if men muſt labour for the bread which endures to everlaſting life, which Chriſt is ſaid to give them, and he not give it, then God of neceſſity muſt deſtroy men for not doing that, which is altogether out of their power to do: for, as for actuall believing, 'tis a work ſo farre out of the power of the creature, as that it requires Gods power Omnipotent to effect. Now to ſay God ſhould deſtroy his creature for want of ſuch an action, as can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be done by any power inferiour to Gods own, which is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite; this is ſo hard a ſaying, and ſo contrary, and riſes up with that fiery conteſtation againſt what the Scripture delivers concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the gratiouſneſſe of the covenant of God, and mercy by Jeſus Chriſt; yea, it ſo riſes up againſt all reaſon &amp; all principles of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſenſe, that there is no Oyle that will mollifie it, no reaſon, nor
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:121088:17"/>argument, nor conſideration, that is able to make attonement for it, or to reconcile it with any of theſe, either with any expreſſion in Scripture concerning the tenour of the grace of God towards the world, nor otherwiſe with the principles of reaſon and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſenſe: 'twere as good reaſon to ſay, that God deſtroyes the creature for not being God, or for not making another Heaven and Earth like to theſe he hath made, as to ſay, he deſtroyeth them for not doing that which they have no more power to doe, then they have to make themſelves God, or an Heaven and Earth.</p>
               <p>Neither will it at all here availe to ſay, that men had power in <hi>Adam,</hi> while as yet in the ſtate of Innocency, then to believe in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> this will not all eaſe the buſineſſe; as if God might in a way of juſtice, equity, and righteouſneſſe, condemne men for not doing that which ſometimes they had power to do, namely, in their firſt Parents though now they have not.</p>
               <p>I anſwer, 'twill not at all eaſe the buſineſſe. Firſt, becauſe 'tis not a truth. Secondly, though it were, yet it would not ſalve the ſore.</p>
               <p>Firſt, that men never had power in <hi>Adam</hi> to believe in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> eſpecially to juſtification, may evidently appear by theſe reaſons: that which <hi>Adam</hi> and himſelf never had in the ſtate of Innocency, that certainly his poſterity could never have: but cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine 'tis, that <hi>Adam</hi> himſelfe had never ſuch power of believing in Chriſt in innocency, neither therefore can his poſterity be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to have ſuch a power.</p>
               <p>Now that he had no ſuch power, is evident hence, becauſe there was no neceſſity, uſe, or occaſion of ſuch a power as this to have been given to <hi>Adam</hi> in that ſtate; we all know and look on God as the moſt wiſe Agent, that ever acted: now 'tis inconſiſtent with his wiſdome and diſpenſation, that he ſhould create ſuch an excellent power as this of believing is, when there was no neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity nor uſe thereof. That there was no occaſion thereof is evident, becauſe during the time of innocency, he was in a ſtate of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe and juſtification on other tearms, and in another way, ſo that he had no neceſſity of a power to believe to juſtification: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. <hi>If righteouſneſſe be by the law, than Chriſt dyed in vaine:</hi> ſo it had been in vain, <hi>Adam</hi> being under a righteouſneſſe by the Law, then for him to believe that Jeſus Chriſt was dead or alive for his juſtification. What's the reaſon man
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:121088:18"/>had no wings put upon him in the time of innocency, but only that he was well enough in that ſtate; for this is reaſon enough to prove that <hi>Adam</hi> had no ſuch power of believing, becauſe well enough without, even in a ſtate of righteouſneſſe.</p>
               <p>Secondly, if <hi>Adam</hi> during his innocency had a power to believe, either for his own, or for any of his poſterity their juſtification and ſalvation, then he had a power alſo to foreſee his fall; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe juſtification preſuppoſes ſinne, becauſe 'tis from ſinne, and conſequently a power to believe, preſuppoſeth a ſight and a ſenſe of ſin: but that he had no ſuch principle in him, vvhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to foreſee his fall in time of innocency, is evident hence; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe had he had a power for to foreſee his fall before he fell; then he had a power or principle out of which he might have been made miſerable, before he ſinned; becauſe it cannot be imagined, but that the foreſight of his ſin and fall, and poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with him, and the whole world, that ſhould come out of his loynes would have been a very tormenting conſideration to him: and therefore it being altogether againſt the righteouſneſſe of God, that man ſhould be miſerable before he ſinned; hence 'tis clear he had no power then to believe in Chriſt, becauſe not able to foreſee his fall.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, if <hi>Adam</hi> in innocency had power to believe in Chriſt, then had he a power to foreſee the incarnation, death, and reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of Chriſt; becauſe none can have a power to believe in Chriſt ſavingly but on knowledge of theſe: now if <hi>Adam</hi> had a power to belive, &amp;c. It muſt be ſuppoſed he had ſuch a know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Chriſts Incarnation, &amp;c. but that he had nor the leaſt whiſpering of this great Myſterie concerning Chriſt during his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency, is evident, as from other Scriptures, ſo eſpecially from that 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.8, 9. Now certainly if there were any of the <hi>deep</hi> things of God that were of the deepeſt myſtery, that of Chriſts Incarnation was the moſt deep of all things deep, out of the ſphear of the minds of Men and Angels; therefore 'tis certain <hi>Adam</hi> had no knowledge of this myſterie till after his fall. But another Objection.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object </seg>
                  </label> He had a power to believe in Chriſt, had this myſtery been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed to him in his innocency, though he had not ſuch a power actually to put it forth, yet had not he ſuch a principle, that had it
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:121088:18"/>been revealed, he had been enabled by a principle within him to have believed.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw </seg>
                  </label> To ſay that <hi>Adam</hi> had any power to believe any thing, but what was ſome way neceſſary and ſitting for him to believe, whether revealed or not, this reflects on the wiſdome of God.</p>
               <p>Now firſt, that it was not neceſſary for him to believe in Chriſt, was touched before, being in a ſtate of juſtification, ſo that it had been impertinent; but had it befitted him, then certainly ſuch a revealing ſhould not have been with held by God; 'tis not to be believed that any thing ſhould have been denied <hi>Adam</hi> eſpecially in point of knowledge, to hinder him from acting any thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient for him to do; and therefore doubtleſſe there was no ſuch power in <hi>Adam</hi> to believe in Chriſt, no nor on this ſuppoſition, That Chriſt had been revealed to him on that condition.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, this is a demonſtrative Argument to prove that <hi>Adam</hi> in innocency had no power to believe in Jeſus Chriſt, becauſe then Chriſt was not given as a covenant to mankinde, and till Chriſt be declared as Gods covenant for juſtification, for <hi>Adam</hi> to have believed in him for juſtification; this had been ſo far from being a likely means to juſtifie, that it had been a preſumption, and more likely to have condemned him: for as it is with the world ſince the covenant of Chriſt hath been revealed; as it would be a very high and fearfull preſumption for any man to wave this covenant, and to betake themſelves to the Lawes righteouſneſſe, or the firſt covenant; ſo on the contrary, during the ſtate of innocency, it had been like preſumption for <hi>Adam,</hi> to have deſerted that covenant of works the righteouſneſſe of the Law, the only covenant then for juſtification, and to have raiſed up another covenant, which he knew nothing of the minde of God, whether believing on him ſhould be juſtification or no.</p>
               <p>Secondly, ſuppoſe it granted, that <hi>Adam</hi> had ſuch a power as we ſpeak of, yet this will not heal the offenſiveneſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of that opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt which we argue; namely, That God deſtroyes man for not doing that, which requires an infinite ſtrength to perform. For firſt, we know God hath made a new covenant of life with man ſince the tranſgreſſion and breach of that covenant, wherein <hi>Adam,</hi> and conſequently all his poſterity ſtood in him, when that power of believing is ſuppoſed to have been in him. Now for God to deprive man of the benefit and bleſſing of that new co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:121088:19"/>and to daſh him as it were in pieces upon the pikes of the old, meerly for a miſpriſion or ſin committed againſt the other, and that ſuch an one which was impoſſible for the creature to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy or redeem himſelf from; this is ſuch a ſaying as is wholly inconſiſtent and deſtructive to the very nature and eſſence of the covenant of grace, as for inſtance. A Noble Family is attainted with High Treaſon againſt the Prince, whereby they are at his mercy for life, liberty, honour, and in this caſe the Prince profeſſes much love to them, and tenderneſſe, and that he is far from taking advantage againſt them, he hath no deſire to deſtroy this Family, yet nevertheleſſe he will not diſcharge them of the attainture, but only upon ſuch and ſuch tearms; now if they were ſuch tearms that neither the Family nor other for them could procure, and yet the Prince profeſſes great care and tenderneſſe, &amp;c. Can any man look on ſuch proceedings as any way gracious: nay, will it not rather expoſe ſuch a Prince to the harder thoughts of men, and had he not better have made uſe of an advantage againſt them, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they have ſo and ſo behaved themſelves againſt him; and he will take the advantage then thus to profeſſe love, and that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires not to take advantage, if they will be redeemed on ſuch and ſuch tearms, which yet are impoſſible for them to performe: as to demand of them to catch all the fiſhes in the ſea, and all the fowles of the aire, and make a preſent of them to him; alas all the world will eaſily ſee, here is not the leaſt touch of any ſuch gratious diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition in him, what ever he pretends. So thoſe that will make the ſaving tearms of the Goſpell ſo hard and impoſſible to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by men, that though they ſhould ſtrive, and endeavour, and riſe to the utmoſt pitch of all that they are able to performe; yet they that ſay they may do all theſe and yet God no way accept of them, nor they never the nearer the grace and favour of God, doubtleſſe they repreſent this new covenant of grace and mercy which God hath made with the world, with as much diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage and reproach, as thoſe tearms which we ſpeak of, of the Prince would be.</p>
               <p>If I were of the judgement of <hi>Arminius</hi> about the point of Free-will, and were to debate the point before men any whit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious. I would deſire no greater advantage againſt him that is mine Adverſary, be he who he will, if he would maintaine his judgement in a way of oppoſition to me thus, That let men doe
<pb facs="tcp:121088:19"/>their utmoſt all their lives, yet they are never the nearer, nor have the more aſſurance of grace and favour; howſoever happily I ſhould be never the nearer any demonſtrative proof, yet I could have this advantage, to put my opinion into a dreſſe ten times more plauſible and conſiſtent with the underſtanding of reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men, then that opinion with all the colours or arguments that may be put upon it.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that power in <hi>Adam</hi> to believe (ſuppoſing 'twere granted he had ſuch) can be no ſufficient ground to juſtifie God in point of equity in the condemnation of them that do their utmoſt that they are able, becauſe Juſtice and Equity ſtands in a Geome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricall &amp; not Arithmeticall proportion, as for inſtance. We know our Saviour ſaith, the Widow that caſt in her two Mites, caſt in more then all, who yet are ſaid to caſt in great ſums, and matters of great value, becauſe they caſt in out of their ſuperfluity, but ſhe caſting in two Mites, caſt in all her ſubſtance: how caſt ſhe in more then they all? that is in a Geometricall proportion; that is, more in conſideration, all things conſidered; that is, more for her to caſt in, then thoſe great ſums for men of eſtate to caſt in; more for commendation, not more abſolutely and ſimply. So the Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the Talent, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.22. the Maſter putting forth his Talents to his Servants, gave the ſame commendation to the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant that gained but two Talents, as to him that gained five; and the reaſon was Geometricall; there was as much reaſon why he that had but two Talents to gain withall, ſhould be commended for gaining two more, as he that had fire for gaining other five; becauſe there was as much diligence required in him to gaine two Talents more, as for the other to make five more by way of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe: and the generall rule in Scripture in ſuch caſes as theſe and the like is, that where much is given, much is required, where little given, little required, where nothing at all given, nothing at all required: ſo that God accepts a man accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to what he hath, and not what he hath not. Now ſuppoſe it granted, that <hi>Adam,</hi> and in him all his poſterity during the time of Innocency, had a power to have believed in Chriſt; yet in a Geometricall conſideration of juſtice and equity it may be more for a man now, though he hath not the like power of believing in Chriſt, yet to do the utmoſt that he is able towards believing; this may be of more value and conſideration in the ſight of God, then
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:121088:20"/>the putting forth an act of believing in Chriſt, where ſuch a power was.</p>
               <p>Alas, granting a power in <hi>Adam</hi> in innocency to have believed, his believing had been but like the caſting in of the rich men, he had done it out of his abundance; but for men in their lapſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition under the preſſure of ſo many indiſpoſitions, yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to give out the utmoſt of their ſtrength and power to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and that by conflicting with incumbrances; this had been more inconſideration, then a believing right-down in <hi>Adam:</hi> and ſo we have the firſt reaſon; if God ſhould deſtroy men after doing all that is in their power to do, he ſhould deſtroy them for not do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a work peculiar to his own Arme.</p>
               <p>Another reaſon in a word; if men may put forth themſelves in their utmoſt power to cloſe with God in the Goſpel, and yet not finde grace with him, ſo far as to be endued with ſtrength from on high to believe, then a man may everlaſtingly be deſtroyed of God, for want of an executive power, or of a principle or power where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to act, without any miſcarriage or ſinfulneſſe at all in the will; whereas the Scripture from place to place, placeth the cauſe of the equity of Gods proceedings in condemnation ſtill upon the will of man, or on ſome corruptions found therein, or on the froward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, perverſeneſſe, and pride in the will, <hi>Luke</hi> 13.34. <hi>Oh Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, &amp;c. thon wouldeſt not;</hi> 'tis not caſt on any impotency in them, not upon any want of power, but the cauſe is in the depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of their will.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.40. <hi>Ye will not come, &amp;c.</hi> He charges not the Jewes with not having power, but they had no will or minde to do it, they ſtood off in fiery oppoſition againſt believing in Chriſt, and comming to him for juſtification.</p>
               <p>So <hi>Acts</hi> 7.51. <hi>A stiffe-necked generation, ye have alwayes reſisted the Holy Ghoſt:</hi> now hovv did they reſiſt the Holy Ghoſt which he charged as the main article of their condemnation; they reſiſt not by any defectiveneſſe of power, but by frowardneſſe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperateneſſe of will, and reſolution in that kinde.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 8.12. and again <hi>Jur.</hi> 44. <hi>We will walk after our own devices, &amp;c.</hi> This ſhevves Gods judgement on them vvas from the fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvardneſſe of their vvill; ſo, <hi>Why will ye dye O ye houſe of Iſrael.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 44.17. <hi>But we will do, &amp;c.</hi> And Chriſt ſaith, <hi>The works of your Father ye will doe:</hi> ye ſhall ſtill ſee that the partition-vvall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſing
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:121088:20"/>betvveen the creature and his peace and acceptation vvith God, ſtill lyes in the crookedneſſe and perverſeneſſe of the heart and vvill.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object </seg>
                  </label> But wherein differs this Tenent you maintain from that <hi>Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> Tenent of Free-will, or how will you anſwer thoſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, denying a power to come to Chriſt. <hi>John</hi> 6.44. <hi>No man can come, &amp;c.</hi> Againe <hi>verſe</hi> 65. <hi>No man can come, &amp;c. John</hi> 12.39. <hi>Therefore ye do not believe becauſe Eſay propheſied, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw </seg>
                  </label> To the former I anſwer; That the <hi>Arminian</hi> opinion of Free-will doth not only differ, and that all the Heaven over, from the one end to the other, from all that hath been aſſerted but it oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes it, and that in two particulars of main conſequence.</p>
               <p>For firſt of all, that places not only a ſufficiency of executive power in a man, to do all things in a ſaving manner towards his believing, but likewiſe a ſufficiency of power in the will, whereby man by the ordinary concurrence of Gods providence may draw out that power to the utmoſt of it.</p>
               <p>That opinion of Free-will doth not aſſert a ſufficiency of execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive power to do ſuch things unto which grace is annexed by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, but they place that whole in ſuch a power in the will, which is able to produce this executive power into action, and that to the utmoſt.</p>
               <p>Secondly, it not only places an executive and willing power to do what they conceive requiſite on mans part towards believing in Chriſt, but further places ſuch a power in man in both kinds, as without any ſupernaturall aſſiſtance, is able to produce a ſaving act of faith in the ſoule.</p>
               <p>Now the thing aſſerted clearly denies both theſe. For firſt though it affirmes a ſufficiency of power for ſuch things as are requiſite on mans part, ſo far to proceed and meet with grace and accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet nevertheleſſe it denies any ſuch power in the will to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce this executive power into act.</p>
               <p>Secondly, it places neither one kinde of power or other, vvhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the creature is enable vvithout a ſupernaturall aſſiſtance from God, to raiſe any ſaving act in the ſoule; ſo that here are too main and moſt conſiderable differences betvveen the one and the other.</p>
               <p>But vvhat difference make vve, betvven that vve call an execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive povver and vvilling povver, or a principle in man to dravv out that other povver.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:121088:21"/>
               <p>The difference betvveen theſe is not hard at all to conceive, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in ordinary diſcourſe vve uſe to make ſuch a diſtinction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a mans power to do ſuch a thing, and his willingneſſe and inclination. There are many rich men that have power and abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to contribute largely to the publick cauſe of the Kingdome, yet nevertheleſſe are far from acting that power, becauſe they have that malignancy in their will, and gainſayingneſſe againſt that action, that that executive power doth them little ſervice in this kinde, towards the ſafety of the State.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 17.16. <hi>Why is there a price in the hand of a Fooll, and no heart to improve it:</hi> what's that price, 'tis the oportunity or exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutive power to do ſuch a thing whereby he might intereſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in the grace of God; and what's the heart he wants, nothing elſe but an inclination or gracious and holy diſpoſition in the will to give that price; that is, to act thoſe things which he hath a power in his hand to do: ſo likewiſe a carnall covetous, voluptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man, hath an executive power to foregoe his ſenſuall courſes and ſet up religious duties in his family, and to attend the means of grace as diligently as any; but what hinders them that they are never the nearer doing, even becauſe there is a malignancy and averſeneſſe in their will againſt ſuch purpoſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object </seg>
                  </label> Doe not thoſe whom we call <hi>Arminians,</hi> hold and maintaine, that covetous and voluptuous perſons have a diſpoſition and incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation in their will to abandon and leave thoſe courſes wherein they are ingaged, and frame themſelves to better: this ſeems ſo unreaſonable, that we cannot conceive that they ſhould have an an inclination in their will to relinquiſh them, and turn to the contrary.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw </seg>
                  </label> For anſwer, 'tis true, they do not maintain, that ſuch perſons whiles living in ſuch courſes, have the bent, and frame, or diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of their will ſtanding ſo, as to abandon the one and take up the other; but they hold, that notwithſtanding the preſent bent of their wils to the contrary, yet that they have a ſufficiency of pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in themſelves, as of knowledge, underſtanding, &amp;c. to unbend their will from ſuch their courſes, and to implant inclinations in themſelves to the contrary: there is no ſuch inclination in their hearts to evill, but that there is a ſufficiency of power in every kinde to unbend their wils from that wherein they now ſtand; and ſo to deſtroy that diſpoſition in them, and plant their wils
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:121088:21"/>with other inclinations, ſuch as are meet to comply with ſpirituall and holy things. Whereas the opinion pleaded for, acknowledges no ſuch power in men, whereby the will being deſperately evill, ſhould be able without any extraordinary hand of God to turne head on it ſelf, and to ſlay thoſe ſinfull propenſions now reigning, and to ſet up the contrary.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object </seg>
                  </label> But what ſhall we ſay to the Scripture laſt mentioned, which ſeems to place the cauſe of mens periſhing in a defectiveneſſe of power, and not in any weakneſſe in their will?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw </seg>
                  </label> For what Chriſt ſpeaks in that <hi>John</hi> 6.44. <hi>No man can come, &amp;c.</hi> The meaning is, no man hath or can have any ſuch principle of deſire, or any ſuch inclination wrought in him, which will ſo far carry and prevaile with him to put forth himſelf in any ſuch way, or hold on in any ſuch courſe, wherein God hath determined and promiſed to meet men with his grace, except it be given him from on high; except my Father, &amp;c. interpoſe with ſome greater power then ordinary, <hi>no man can come to me,</hi> no man hath any foreſight of any compleat power of comming to me, except my Father interpoſe in it; for that is one thing would be taken ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all notice of, that there may be ſaid to be a double power in a man in reference to ſuch and ſuch effects.</p>
               <p>The firſt we may call a perfect and compleat power; that is, ſuch a power that hath all things as it were by it to reduce it ſelfe into act; that we call a compleat and perfect power of the will: the other is an incompleat and imperfect power; which is this: that though there be a ſufficiency of power in relation to ſuch an effect in one kinde, yet nevertheleſſe there is a defectiveneſſe of power in another kinde, and this is call'd a power to do a thing, becauſe there is a ſufficiency of power to do the thing in one kind, yet nevertheleſſe call'd a defective incompleat power, becauſe it hath not all things at hand, which are requiſite to reduce it into act. As for example, when a man hath a large eſtate, he hath wherewith to live generouſly, but yet this is but an incompleat power, if he hath no other; for 'tis not a fulneſſe of eſtate that will help him to doe it; if he hath a penurious diſpoſition in him: alas he is never the nearer to ſuch a compleat life: but if to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with a full eſtate, he hath an ingenuous diſpoſition; now there is a compleat and perfect power in a man to live freely; and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:121088:22"/>ſo we know there are many ſuch expreſſions in Scripture.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If thou wilt thou canſt make me cleane:</hi> now there is a plaine difference between Chriſts will and power: and 'tis very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable that the Scripture it ſelfe uſes both kinde of expreſſions, ſpeaking both wayes; ſometimes giving the n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me of power to a meer executive power, when as there is no will in conjunction to reduce to act, And againe, another while there is not a will ſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to an executive power, he denies the very name of a power to him, and this it doth both ſpeaking of God and Man.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 3. <hi>verſ.</hi> 9. <hi>God is able of theſe ſtones to raiſe up children:</hi> here <hi>Iohn</hi> aſſerts a power to God to raiſe up &amp;c. But yet there was no will in God to do it. Againe, when there is not a willingneſſe in God to do a thing, there the Scripture denies ſo much as a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to him: as 'tis ſaid of Chriſt, he could do no great works there, becauſe of their unbelief. Now there was an executive power in Chriſt, rich and full; whereby to have wrought any great miracle there; but becauſe he had no will, therefore 'tis ſaid he had not power, meaning no compleatneſſe of power, which requires a ſufficiency of executive power, and a ſufficiency of will and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination to put that power into act. And ſo we ſee the like ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions uſed, when the Scripture ſpeaks of men, ſometime it cals that by the name of power to do a thing, which is only an executive power. <hi>Gen.</hi> 13.29. <hi>Tis in the power of mine hand to do thee hurt,</hi> that is, a ſufficiency of ſtrength. <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Have not I power to eat and drink, &amp;c.</hi> that is, we are provided with an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutive power.</p>
               <p>But in other places we ſhall ſee where there is a ſufficiency of power in this kinde the Holy Ghoſt denies a ſufficiency of power. <hi>John</hi> 1.3, 9. <hi>Cannot ſinne.</hi> Now he that is moſt born of God and deepeſt baptized in the Spirit of Grace and holineſſe, hath an exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutive power to commit ſin as well as any; but becauſe he hath no diſpoſition thereto, therefore the Scripture denies he hath power to do it, he hath no compleat power to reduce that power into act.</p>
               <p>2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.8. <hi>For we can do nothing againſt the truth, but for it;</hi> they had an executive power to have uttered words of excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, but we can do nothing, &amp;c. That is, his will was averſe from making any ſuch uſe of his power, thereby to act any thing that might hinder the couſe of the Goſpel.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:121088:22"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 22.38. Said <hi>Balaam, Have I any power to do any thing;</hi> that is, have I any will or any ground or reaſon, to be willing to ſay any evill which thou wouldeſt have me: for otherwiſe he had power enough to pronounce any curſe; any evill ſpeaking againſt Gods children, but no ground or reaſon to incline him.</p>
               <p>And ſo we ſee in the cloſe of all, in what conſideration the aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion laid down is neceſſary to be maintained; without maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whereof, we ſhall repreſent Gods proceedings in the Covenant of grace; as a moſt unreaſonable and hard ſaying; as ſuch a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant that hath neither truth, nor grace, nor uprightneſſe in it; but that men ſhould be deſtroyed without any malignancy at all in their wils, meerly for a bare impotency or want of power in them, to do that which is out of their power to do.</p>
               <p>'Twas the ſaying of <hi>Auguſtine</hi> long ſince, take away mens wils and take away Hell and all; ſo that it muſt be ſome ſin com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againſt this ſecond Covenant of grace after the breach of the firſt, which muſt daſh men in pieces upon the point of their will. Now there can be nothing that hath the nature of ſin in it, but that which hath the influence and concurrence of the will in it. Many other things relating hereto have been ſpoken of in a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute lately.</p>
               <p>Now the uſe of what hath been ſpoken is this; That ſince 'tis ſo eaſie to expoſe the wayes of God, and his proceedings in wayes of condemnation, to the reproaches and calumnies of thoſe that are enemies to the truth, by hard, unquoth, and unwarrantable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions; though perhaps for the ſubſtance of the thing, that which is ſaid and aſſerted, is no more but the truth; we ſhould be very carefull to ſtudy all manner of expreſſions, and conſult with all manner of Scriptures, if any thing may any way mollifie as it were, that in the proceedings of God, which is apt to ſeem grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous and harſh in the eyes of fleſh and blood.</p>
               <p>And if ſo be we cannot come to expreſſe our ſelves, but that ſtill we ſhall leave the buſineſſe very hard and obnoxious to the Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, we ſhall rather excuſe our ſelves after ſome ſuch manner as this is, that God hath not given us that ability of utterance and expreſſions, and that we conceive the buſineſſe better in our mindes, then we are able to give account of to others, but we ſhall mightily diſadvantage the truth, and cauſe the enemies to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:121088:23"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:121088:23"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:121088:24"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:121088:25"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:121088:25"/>lift up their Horn on high, if ſo be we ſhal maintain or profeſſe any truth of God in any ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> me, and hard and gift vou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as make an unacceptable found in the ears of men.</p>
               <p>Doubtleſſe the Scriptures, if ſo be God would but acc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> with thoſe that are proper for ſuch an occaſion and ſervice as this is, it ſpeaks of all the wayes and dealings of God with men, even thoſe that ſeem ſo hard to fleſh and blood, ſo as to ſtop the mouths of all Adverſaries, that are ready to take advantage from them, and cry out againſt the truth; and therefore they that deſire to ſtand up in the cauſe of God, and to plead the truth of God, they muſt be carefull, and take pains how to expreſſe themſelves in ſuch points, except they be able ſome way to qualifie and ſoften the hardneſſe of it; otherwiſe they ſhall diſadvantage more then ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage it.</p>
               <div type="witness_statements">
                  <p>A ſecond Copie of which Sermon commended by SAM. LAN<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to the peruſall of Mr. LAURENCE STEELE, is thus ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed: <hi>I have peruſed it over, and finde nothing contrary to my own Copie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A third Copie alſo is ſubſcribed by Mr. JOHN WEEKES thus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Sir, <hi>I have peruſed this Copie, I finde it to be the ſame with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> for the mains, only it is taken more largely.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="letter">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:121088:25"/>
               <head>The Second Letter to Mr. <hi>J. G.</hi> In Reply to the SERMON.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Much respected Sir,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">U</seg>Pon failing in my expectation, of your peruſing that Copy of your Sermon, preached <hi>April</hi> 28. 1644. being the Sabbath next after my giving you in two Sheets of writing (which Copy I left at your houſe the night before your journeying, about <hi>May</hi> 15.) I ſince have commended Copies thereof to the ſtrict view of ſome of your knowne hearers and writers; who upon comparing it with their Noats, finde it exactly to agree with what you delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: which the rather I took care to do, becauſe (as I ſignified in my Noat left for you, with that Copy the night forementioned) I found by the meer reading, and writing that Copy (which alone I had then done) that 'twas mainly intended by way of anſwer to the Objections in thoſe two ſheets preſented; and upon further peruſall, I finde you intend it for a full and perfect anſwer: wherein you give <hi>two Arguments,</hi> which you affirme, are <hi>for the clearing of the whole buſineſſe,</hi> being for vindication of your fifth aſſertion oppoſed, and afterwards you endeavour to clear it from the opinion of Free-will, and that becauſe 'tis charged there to be the ſame with a maine maxime of the <hi>Arminians</hi> there expreſt, yea, I can conclude no leſſe from your very next Sermon follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, preached <hi>May</hi> 5. wherein, without the leaſt intimation of any Objections behind not cleared. You intimated your clearing the matter from all Objections, and ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>upon proceeded to new matter; and that notwithſtanding the Friday b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fore; being <hi>May</hi> 3. upon my ſpeech with you about thoſe Obje<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ions, you informed me, that in peruſall you were much ſtraitned in time, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, at my deſire, you ſeemed to promiſe further conſideration.</p>
               <p>And for as much as I finde, that mine end in that diſcourſe gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven you in being wholly for the truths advantage, inſtead of being
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:121088:26"/>accompliſhed is perverted, in that you have thence taken occaſion after a grievous manner to defame that truth, which is there grounded on ſundry Scriptures againſt your errour: I count <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> meet to wards the attaining that firſt end, to endeavour the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation thereof againſt all aſperſions caſt upon it; elſe will my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer endeavour continue very injurious to that truth, which it was intended to advantage.</p>
               <p>Wherein, before my vindicating the main matter, I cannot but take notice of one paſſage; that whereas upon your inlargements about your fifth Aſſertion, you gave ſuch an expoſition upon <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Dead in ſinnes, &amp;c.</hi> as is at large proved contradictory to evident reaſon: yet about the beginning of that clearing Sermon, you rehint the ſame, in theſe words <hi>[Dead in ſinnes, &amp;c. in ſuch a ſenſe, as was formerly explained,]</hi> and that without the leaſt ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle for its vindication.</p>
               <p>Another thing to be obſerved, is your expreſſion touching your fifth Aſſertion, which you ſay in the beginning of that Sermon, is <hi>[one paſſage which it ſeems ſome did not ſo clearly underſtand]</hi> and afterwards <hi>[which ſome could not ſo well underſtand or compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend;]</hi> by which you make the ground of all the Controverſie, to be a miſ-underſtanding; whereas you repeat the ſame in theſe very expreſſions wherein 'twas oppoſed, as namely, thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That if men will be willing to do unfeinedly what God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed them in a way of nature, God hath promiſed ſucceſſe and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation in this way:</hi> yea, ſoon after recited thus, <hi>Men putting forth themſelves to do according to what God hath inabled them to do in a way of nature, God will meet them with grace and acceptation.</hi> Yea, moſt plainly reitrerated in your after ſhewing the difference between this, and the opinion of Free-will, in theſe words. <hi>Their opinion aſſerts not a ſufficiency of executive power to do ſuch things as whereto grace is annexed by promiſe.</hi> By which you di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſifie your opinion from theirs, clearly ſhewing, that <hi>Your opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion aſſerts a power to do ſuch things, as whereto grace is annexed by promiſe,</hi> which are the very tearms oppoſed; now it is hard to conceive, how I ſhould miſ-underſtand, in oppoſing your expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions ſo often given: whereof you give one various expreſſion; namely, <hi>That if men do their utmoſt, &amp;c. they ſhall have anſwerable ſucceſſe:</hi> which expreſſion directly overthrowes your Tenent, <hi>That man may ſo do, as to ingage God to give grace;</hi> for if upon
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:121088:26"/>improvement God gives anſwerable ſucceſſe, then certainly he gives not ſaving-grace; for there is an infinite diſproportion and unanſwerableneſſe betweene mans naturall improvement, and Gods ſuperadding ſupernatur all grace: ſuch ſhall have anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſucceſſe; namely, in reſpect of naturall indowments, they ſhall have the uſe of their naturals continued, augmented, and ſhall not be given up to vile affections, which <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.26. is the puniſhment of abuſers of naturals, but this is far ſhort of ſaving-grace, which you make to be but ſucceſſe anſwerable. Having therefore recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved abundant confirmation that I no way miſ-underſtood the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, I ſhall now take boldneſſe to proceed; wherein, as God ſhall aſſiſt me, I ſhall endeavour to ſound the depths of thoſe two grand clearing Arguments, ſuppoſing, that if God ſhall inable me to levell thoſe Mountaines lying in the way of mine aſſertion al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged againſt your errour, there will need no further attone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for that which you make utterly incurable by any mediation of reaſon, conſideration, diſtinction, project, &amp;c. one or other: Towards vindication of which mine aſſertion, (namely, <hi>That men naturally have not power to do ſuch things, as whereto God hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed grace;</hi>) I conceive it very meet here to premiſe a very perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Obſervation, which I received from your ſelfe, in a Sermon preached <hi>June</hi> 12.1639. at <hi>Caple;</hi> on <hi>John</hi> 20.31. wherein, when you came to anſwer Objections, you premiſed this conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, <hi>When men have a truth well grounded on Scripture, though they ſhould meet with a thouſand objections, which they could not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, yet they muſt not therefore caſt away the truth, if they can ſee it through them all, becauſe it is eaſier to obſcure and ſhadow many truths by objections, then to clear one truth from all objections.</hi> See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therefore the tenent to be vindicated, hath been bottomed on many Arguments from Scripture, I may not in the leaſt queſtion that truth, till thoſe Scripture-grounds be deſtroyed, and whether you do not rather ſhadow a truth then oppoſe an errour, in that you deſtroy not one Argument of many, though from Scripture, but only produce two remote Arguments to prove the neceſſity of your errour, this I commend to any impartiall tryall: as alſo whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther two Arguments alleadged, to arraign and condemne the equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and righteouſneſſe of Gods proceedings according to his Word (though not to all croſſe reaſonings) be ſufficient to deſtroy the truth of his Word.</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:121088:27"/>
               <p>Which being premiſed, I ſhall in Gods Name make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> againſt thoſe two Arguments, at leaſt, as they oppoſe the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> pleaded for.</p>
               <p>Firſt then, for the firſt reaſon; <hi>If men muſt labour, &amp;c. Then God must deſtroy man for not doing that which is altogether <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of his power to doe:</hi> which conſequence you count <hi>moſt abſurd, ſenſeleſſe,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Touching which conſequence ſo exploded, <hi>That God deſtroyes, &amp;c.</hi> that this is fully agreeable with <hi>Gods juſtice, grace; &amp;c.</hi> which you ſay, <hi>it ſo oppoſeth,</hi> I ſhall prove clearly from your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> words in your ſecond reaſon following, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That the Scripture placeth the cauſe of the equity of Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings in condemnation ſtill upon mans will, or on ſome corrupt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, frowardneſſe, or perverſeneſſe found therein.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whence it thus followes; if it be equity in God no condg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> man for the ſinfulneſſe of his will, then God may in equity con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne man for not doing that which is altogether out of his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to do; but the former you hold and prove true from Scriptures the latter therefore, that God may in equity condemne man, for not doing that which is altogether out of his power to do, inevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably followes, becauſe to purifie or rectifie mans will, is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of mans power to do; w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> thing you peremptorily aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> againſt the tenent of Free-will: ſo then, that God deſtroyes men for not doing that, which is altogether beyond their power to do (which here you make <hi>ſo abſure, unjuſt, &amp;c.</hi>) this is a direct conſequent upon your own enſuing reaſon; yea, this very reaſon proves, that Gods deſtroying man to, is an act of <hi>justice and equity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object </seg>
                  </label> But yet you further objected in diſcourſe, <hi>That God deſtroyes man, not ſo much for not willing ſavingly, as for the obſtinacy of his naturall will.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw </seg>
                  </label> For anſwer whereto; firſt, this diſtinction between <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g ſavingly, and obſtinacy of will,</hi> on which you ground the Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is of no force at all: for he that wils not ſavingly, is obſtinate in his will: ſo <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.7. <hi>The carnall minds,</hi> or the minding of the fleſh, <hi>is enmity againſt God:</hi> which tearm <hi>fleſbly winde,</hi> being there oppoſed to the <hi>spirituall minds,</hi> takes in every mind that is not ſpirituall; yea, it includes the will, being a chieſe part of the minde: and ſo every naturall will without exception, is en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>y,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:121088:27"/>or obſtinacy &amp; perverſeneſſe, all which, the tearm enmity imports; ſo then God deſtroying man for not willing ſavingly, doth deſtroy for obſtinacy of will.</p>
               <p>Or ſecondly, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ther God deſtroy for enmity of minde, and ſo of will, or whether for not willing ſavingly, or according to the expreſſion in that Text, for <hi>not ſubjecting it ſelf to the Law of God;</hi> ſtill he deſtroyes man for not doing that, which is altogether out of his power to do, which is clear from the end of that ſeventh Verſe; where the reaſon of the mindes, and therein of the wils obſtinacy, and of its not becomming ſubject to Gods law is added, in theſe words, <hi>becauſe it cannot,</hi> or becauſe it hath not power, namely to become ſubject, or to ſubject it ſelfe to Gods Law: It muſt therefore be concluded, that God deſtroying man upon any of your tearmes, whether for not willing ſavingly, or for obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy, perverſeneſſe, &amp;c. doth deſtroy man for not doing that which is altogether out of his power to do; and conſequently, that according to your own grounds, you inevitably plunge your ſelfe into that very pit of abſurdity, which you digg'd; yea, into ſuch an Abyſſe, as whereout you conclude, <hi>No mediation of reaſon, project, &amp;c. can redeeme:</hi> yea, by your very tearms, the juſtice and equity of God, in ſuch a deſtroying of man, is undeniably con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed: By which reaſons, ſtriking ſo directly the root of your firſt Argument, I conceive tis clearly removed: nevertheleſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there are ſuch ſtrong holds raiſed to ſtand by it, I ſhall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to what power God ſhall vouchſafe me, aſſault thoſe alſo.</p>
               <p>Wherein, for thoſe high aſperſions caſt upon the conſequent of that opinion, which oppoſeth yours, which you make <hi>ſo contrary to the tenour, truth of the Goſpel, &amp;c.</hi> comparing theſe with what you ſay after in the concluſion, that <hi>[perhapſe for the ſubſtance of it, tis no more then the truth]</hi> which you give as your finall ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence paſt upon the ſame opinion, I cannot but judge that here you little thought what you ſhould ſpeak after, and at the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, you quite forgot what you had ſaid before. But that <hi>ſuch a ſaying riſes up with ſuch contradiction againſt Gods juſtice, grace, &amp;c. as no principles of reaſon, common ſenſe, &amp;c. can reconcile, &amp;c.</hi> this ſhall, yea muſt be granted you, yet all ſo far from the leaſt diſparaging its truth, as that it ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> have meat out of this eater: for could the heights and depths of Gods juſtice in wayes of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation be compaſt about by the reaſon and comprehenſions of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:121088:28"/>men, yea or Angels, they could not be themſelves incomprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, whoſe judgments are paſt finding out; therefore to ſay they are without the line or ſphear of the largeſt created underſtanding, is to give them their due valuation: whereas, to ſay that cannot be juſtice in God, which no reaſon can reach, this is to make his juſtice comprehenſible, and that we muſt believe nothing of Gods wayes above our reaſon.</p>
               <p>And whereas you affirme, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t were as good reaſon to ſay, God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyes man for not being God, &amp;c. as for not believing, becauſe man can no more do the one, then the other, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt if it be granted, that man hath no more power to believe, then to become God, &amp;c. it followes not therefore, that us as good reaſon to deſtroy man for not being God, or for not creating, as for not believing; for in <hi>Adam</hi> (<hi>in whom</hi> you after-ſay, <hi>all his poſterity ſtood</hi>) man, in order to his perfect happineſſe, had a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to performe what ever might have been by God commanded (for without ſuch a power man-kind, in <hi>Adam,</hi> could not have had power to ſtand happy, but had at beſt bin ſiable to miſery, by diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, and that through impotency ſeeing therefore, that while he could haue ſtood in a ſtate of life, he prophanly changed it for a ſtate of death, with moſt reaſon might God require him, to doe as much for recovering his happines, after loſt by his own tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as before for continuing it, and ſo may require any act from him (whether faith or any other) who was at firſt created with a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er correſpondent; but contrarily, man never had power to be God, nor to create, &amp;c. Therefore 'tis not a like reaſonable, to require him to become God, for his recovery, as to believe. Again, 'tis denied, that man hath no more power at all to believe, then to make himſelf God, &amp;c. For there is ſuch a power in man as may be made a meet ſubject to receive, and cloſe with Gods work of faith; but man is not made a ſubject capable of the Godhead, nor of the ſupremacy of creation.</p>
               <p>Next then, to proceed to the chiefe queſtion, <hi>whether Adam in innocency had a power of believing, or not.</hi> Touching which controverſie it ſeems moſt neceſſary to conſider ſtrictly, what 'twas for him to have ſuch a power, or wherein it truly conſiſts, that we confound not our ſelves by compounding it with ſome other thing; becauſe if we conſider not what 'tis ſimply in it felt, we may conceive it not to be, where 'tis; becauſe ſome other
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:121088:28"/>power or thing, taken, or indeed miſtaken for it, may not be there alſo: Concerning which, a power of believing (according to your own definition) may be ſaid to be that, whereby the ſoule is inabled cordially to aſſent to, or intirely to cloſe, with what God ſhall reveale to be believed. Which cordiall aſſenting you ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound to be an act which the whole heart cloſeth with, even <hi>the understanding, will, and affections,</hi> as in your Sermon forementio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, preached at <hi>Caple,</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>John</hi> 20.31. Which act of cloſing, whether it may be taken in, without an act of recumbency, which you then underſtood to be immediately, and as it were inſeparably following, or elſe, as eſſentially comprehending an act of recum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bency; this needs not be queſtioned here, both agreeing in this, that a power of believing is a power of entire cloſing with things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed, and whether only to be cloſed with, as true, or vvith re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lying alſo, this rather concernes the manner of propounding or revealing, though to follow your definition would be greater ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to me; which laid dovvn, may be very uſefull tovvards the matter in doubt.</p>
               <p>As firſt, for your firſt reaſon againſt <hi>Adam</hi> having ſuch a povver, becauſe <hi>no neceſſity thereof, &amp;c.</hi> ſuppoſe it granted, that he had no need to believe; yet this proves not his not having a povver, for the uſe or need of a povver given not eſſence to it, nor is it the eſſence thereof; there may be a povver to do vvhere no need is, elſe a man hath not povver to do any thing vvhereof he hath not, need; as not a povver to vvalk, ſpeak, &amp;c. becauſe no need: vvhereas a man hath povver to do thouſands of acts needleſſe, and God hath a povver to <hi>raiſe of ſtones children unto Abraham,</hi> though it be a needleſſe vvork. So that povver is here miſ-under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood in making povver and need to believe, vvhich are tvvo evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently diſtinct things to be in one individuall.</p>
               <p>But ſecondly, by vvay of exception againſt your Argument, <hi>that becauſe he needed not to believe to juſtification, therefore he needed not a power to believe.</hi> This conſequence may be denied thus.</p>
               <p>If there may be need and uſe of believing this myſterie, in or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong ſuch as have no need, nor uſe thereof unto juſtification; then <hi>Adams</hi> not having need or uſe of believing to juſtification, cannot prove his not needing to have believed at all. But the former is true, vvitneſſe the Angel <hi>Gabriel, Luke.</hi> 1.26. Who having no need, nor uſe of believing to juſtification, had yet need and uſe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:121088:29"/>thereof for the teſtifying the truth of this myſterie, vvhich he could not have done without a true believing it himſelf. The like might be proved from that company of Angels ſolemnizing CHRISTS birth, with a ſong ſo befitting it, <hi>Luke</hi> 2.15. The litter therefore plainly followes, that <hi>Adams</hi> not having need to believe this my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery unto juſtification, cannot prove that he could not have need to have believed for ſome other end.</p>
               <p>Yea thirdly, and that partly by way of conceſſion, and partly by way of exception, if it be granted, that <hi>Adam</hi> needed not to have believed this myſterie to juſtification, nor for any other end; yet this proves not that he needed not a power to have believed this myſterie: becauſe ſuch a power ſo excellent might be needfull and uſefull to the producing of other acts needfull, though altogether uſeleſſe for this; and that it vvas needfull ſo, appears from the next particular.</p>
               <p>Therefore in the fourth place, the thing to be proved is, that he had both need and uſe of ſuch a power for other ends; that, what you ſay againſt <hi>Gods Wiſdome,</hi> in giving man ſuch a power, may thereby be overthrown; and that he needed ſuch a power, I prove from this your own Argument alleadged to evince the contrary, and that thus: <hi>Adam</hi> ſtanding righteous by the Law of works (which is your Argument) that he might ſo do, could not but need a power of true cloſing with the righteouſneſſe, holineſſe, &amp;c. of God, in every work or command required; for without a right apprehending and acknowledging the excellencies of God, in his commands, he could not have rightly obeyed God in any one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand: whence it follows, that in having need of a power of clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing with the holineſſe, &amp;c. of God in any command, he therein had need of a power of cloſing with the truth, and faithfulneſſe of God in any promiſe, whether of Chriſt, or any other; becauſe the ſelf-ſame power would neceſſarily have inabled him to each of thoſe acts a-like; for it had been impoſſible for <hi>Adam</hi> to have had a power to have acknowledged God in his holineſſe, and not by the ſame to cloſe with his truth and faithfulneſſe; both which go together ſo inſeparably, as that we finde God himſelfe moſt fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently ratifying the promulgation o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> great promiſes by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, by declaring himſelf the holy One, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord the holy one of Iſrael,</hi> clearly intimating, that the true apprehending of Gods holineſſe is ſuch a prevailing argument, as will inforce
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:121088:29"/>men to cloſe with his truth and faithfulneſs touching the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of all his promiſes.</p>
               <p>Yea, for further clearing, <hi>Adam</hi> had not only need, but uſe of a power of believing, as appears from Gods method, in ſtating man in that high office of dominion over the whole creation; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, after God had given him command to bear dominion over all creatures, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.28. he proceeds in the two following verſes to confirme to him that office, by promiſes as large as that command, <hi>Behold I have given to you every Hearb, &amp;c. Which ſhall be to you for meat:</hi> which words are a direct promiſe, in anſwer whereto <hi>Adam</hi> needed a power to believe; becauſe, as God added to the command a promiſe anſwerable, and all as needfull for the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the dominion upon him, ſo vvas it as needfull for <hi>Adam</hi> actually to believe that promiſe, that thereby he might undertake that office, not vvith doubting, but vvith aſſurance of ſucceſſe, which could only be confirmed to him, by a promiſe from the ſole Creator, and Lord over all. Yea, contrarily, if he had not regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that promiſe he had thereby prophaned Gods wiſdome in exhibiting it, and not believing he had oppugned Gods truth and faithfulneſſe touching performance. Seeing then that <hi>Adam</hi> had both need and uſe of a power, whereby to believe the truth, yea, the rich grace of God alſo, in that great promiſe, which confirmed his univerſall Soveraignty over the whole creation, hence it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes that <hi>Adam</hi> had both need &amp; uſe of ſuch a power, as where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he could have believed the myſtery of Chriſt (though he needed not, by that power to believe that myſtery) which may be fully proved from this reaſon, becauſe <hi>Adam</hi> being then upright or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, could not but believe that firſt promiſe of dominion, from a right principle; namely, from a true apprehenſion and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the faithfulneſſe and grace of God, which knowledge (being that ſpring or fountaine, whence a true believing in Chriſt doth alwayes, and can alone flow) <hi>Adam</hi> being furniſhed with, could not but have believed the myſterie of Chriſt; becauſe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by all the Saints have believed: and indeed God acts ſo fully like himſelf, that ſo far as a man knowes, and believes Gods excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies, he cannot but know and believe his revealed acts and contrivances what ever they be: but above all others, the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie of compaſſing ſalvation by Chriſt, holds forth ſo lively a repreſentation of God, in all his excellencies of Wiſdome,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:121088:30"/>grace, righteouſneſſe, &amp;c. as would have enforced <hi>Adam</hi> to have beleeved it, who before had a knowledge of Gods excellen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>, in being created in Gods own image, which conſiſted in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, as alſo in <hi>righteouſneſſe and holineſſe.</hi> By which Arguments, I conceive, that both <hi>Adams</hi> having need, and uſe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> power, as could have produced a beleeving in Chriſt, is evinced; and the Wiſedome of God therein vindicated, the vindication whereof is a work of ſuch concernment as will I hope, excuſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y largeneſſe herein.</p>
               <p>But to proceed both to the ſecond and third reaſon, which are one and the ſame; The firſt, <hi>becauſe he had not power to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>know his fall,</hi> nor ſecondly <hi>Chriſts death, &amp;c.</hi> which Argument may be thus deſtroyed.</p>
               <p>If the eſſence of a power of beleeving conſiſts not at all in the knowledge of Gods Will, before revealed by God, then <hi>Adam</hi> not having power to know the myſtery of Chriſt, before revealed by God, doth no way prove his not having a power of beleeving that myſtery; but the former is true, That the eſſence of a power of beleeving conſiſts not, &amp;c. Becauſe according to your definiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>is a power of cordiall aſſenting to the truth of a promiſe of God, that is to ſay, a promiſe revealed, or propounded, which muſt be preſuppoſed; now a power of cloſing with the truth of what God reveales is far different from a power of fore-know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Gods Will before revealed: for the one, namely the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the <hi>ſecrets</hi> of God <hi>belongs</hi> onely <hi>to God,</hi> while his <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed will belongs to men:</hi> And ſo God gives a power of belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to many thouſands, and yet reſerves his ſecret Councell from them all; the latter alſo, That <hi>Adams</hi> not having power to foreknow, &amp;c. follows inevitably, becauſe when two faculities differ in kind, then the abſence of one proves not at all the abſence of another.</p>
               <p>Next after, you propound an Objection againſt your ſelfe, for Anſwer whereto, you firſt refer to your fore-going argument againſt Gods Wiſdome, which is already anſwered at large, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you cloſe up your anſwer after this manner of reaſoning.</p>
               <p>Firſt, you ſay, <hi>Christ could not be revealed, becauſe not conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, &amp;c.</hi> And thence you infer, that <hi>Therfore doubtles Adam had not a power to have beleeved in Chriſt;</hi> no, <hi>not on this ſuppoſition, That Chriſt had been then revealed to him.</hi> Which Argument is indeed
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:121088:30"/>moſt contradictory, yea utterly deſtructive to it ſelfe: For firſt, you ground <hi>Adams not having ſuch a power</hi> upon this reaſon, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Christ could not be revealed,</hi> and afterwards, you quite de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy that very reaſon, <hi>by ſuppoſing,</hi> or granting <hi>Chriſt to have been revealed:</hi> ſo that in Anſwer to a main and moſt conſiderable objection, you onely repeat a former reaſon, already anſwered, and adde one new, which you immediately deſtroy by your own contra-ſuppoſition, and ſo the Objection remaines altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anſwered.</p>
               <p>Next follows your fourth reaſon, againſt <hi>Adams</hi> having ſuch a power, <hi>becauſe Chriſt was not revealed,</hi> which may be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thus.</p>
               <p>If the want of an outward meanes, though neceſſary to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur in producing an act, cannot prove the want of the intrinſe call power neceſſary to that act, then it follows, That <hi>Adams</hi> wanting the Revelation of the object to be beleeved, cannot prove his wanting an inward power to beleeve: But the former is true, that the want of an outward meanes, &amp;c. cannot prove the inward power wanting, becauſe the outward means, and the inward power are two diſtinct things: for inſtance; food, the outward means of feeding is one thing, and the appetite, the inward facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of receiving food, is another; and therefore the having of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may well conſiſt with the want of either; one man may have an inward faculty of appetite, and want outward food; and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may have outward food, and want an inward receptive fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty: The latter therefore inevitably follows, that <hi>Adams</hi> wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Revelation, &amp;c. proves not his wanting an inward pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, &amp;c. becauſe the Revelation of the object by promiſe, the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward means of beleeving, being one thing; and faith the inward power of receiving it another thing, diſtinct from the former: hence it comes to paſſe, that either of them may be, where either of them is wanting; <hi>Adam</hi> then might have a power of belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and want the word of faith, though now faith comes by hearing even as he was created in Gods image, perfectly at once, though Saints now are transformed into the ſame image gradually and that by means of the Word, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18. and contrarily many now have the Word, and not that power, the Word being not of the eſſence of that power.</p>
               <p>Secondly, another Argument may be this, if <hi>Adam</hi> had not
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:121088:31"/>power to beleeve a thing, or object, becauſe the object was not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed, then 'twill follow that <hi>Adam</hi> had not a power of ſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> righteous by the Law of works, for if he had not power to bel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ve a thing, becauſe 'twas not revealed, then by the ſame reaſon, he had not power at firſt to obey any command, becauſe 'twas not revealed, for the Revelation of a command is as much neceſſary to obeying <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s the Revelation of a promiſe is neceſſary to the beleeving therof; and the meer Revelation of a promiſe would have infuſed into <hi>Adam</hi> no more power of beleeving, then the meer Revelation of a com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nd would have infuſed power of obeying: whence it follows, that <hi>Adam</hi> in his firſt perfection was ſo far from having power to ſtand righteous, by a Law of works, by performing any thing to be commanded, as that indeed, when he was at firſt created, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this your reaſon, he had not then power to obey any command whatſoever, becauſe his creation was fully finiſhed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any command was revealed: yea, from that time forward when ever any command had been revealed, he had ſtood in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eed of ſupply of new power to obey, becauſe before 'twas revealed he had not power to obey. Which conſequences utterly over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw that perfect <hi>power by ſtanding righteous by works,</hi> which you expreſly affirm, <hi>Adam</hi> had, making him unable to perform any work, by his firſt created power.</p>
               <p>Thus much in Anſwer to your reaſons alleadged againſt <hi>Adams</hi> having <hi>power of beleeving, &amp;c.</hi> which are all grounded upon a miſ-underſtanding of, and ſwerving from, the true definition of ſuch a power, and ſo are made up of an indi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tinct, and conſuled conjumbling of other things with it; for neither the need, uſe thereof, nor the fore-knowledge, or Revelation of an object, are at all eſſentially neceſſary to make up ſuch a power, as hath been proved. Touching which matter I muſt adde one word, <hi>viz.</hi> that it muſt needs be dangerous preſumption to charge ſuch a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon with weakneſſe before triall, who for excellency and perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of nature, is avouched again and again by God himſelfe to be created after Gods own Image and likeneſſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. and to be made upright, or righteous, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.29. Yea, eſpecially to ground that charge againſt him upon ſuch reaſons, as wholly tend to prove, that he was not in a capacity of being tryed; whether he had ſuch a power of beleeving or not, by which act the grand Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-peece of Gods whol Creation is without all ground vilified.</p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:121088:31"/>
               <p>Againſt all which, that I may yet adde one paſſage; I ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to ſtate the queſtion in moſt cle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and full tearmes, which queſtion being, <hi>Whether. Adam had a power of beleeving in Chriſt;</hi> (the eſſence of which power conſiſts in a power to beleeve an object revealed) cannot be truely framed, except with this ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, That Chriſt had been revealed, ſo that to go about to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine, much more to determine, what his power was to beleeve an object, without ſuppoſing that object to be revealed; this is a courſe inconſiſtent with the nature of this power, which neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily preſuppoſeth the revelation of an object, for the tryall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: for though ſuch a power may be without an outward Object yet there can be no tryall of its being without it, as a man may have an inward appetite, but we cannot rightly examine his having it, but by giving him outward food, which queſtion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore may be fairly propounded thus, <hi>Whether Adam had a power of believing Chriſt, ſuppoſing, Christ had been revealed?</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer whereto muſt be this, That he could not but have ſuch a power, it being eſſentially neceſſary to his ſtate of perfection, as appeares by theſe three conſequences.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Firſt, becauſe without it, upon the revealing of Chriſt (which is here ſuppoſed) <hi>Adam</hi> muſt have been miſerable by oppoſing the truth of God in that promiſe, and that through want of power.</item>
                  <item>Or ſecondly, if upon the revelation of this myſtery, he had not had power to have beleeved it, then neceſſarily he muſt have, needed ſupply of new power, whereby to have beleeved, and ſo upon this revelation (ſuppoſed) his condition, would have been the very condition of unbeleevers now, who upon the revealing of this myſtery need new power to beleeve it; both which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences are utterly inconſiſtent with the nature of his firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat power of ſtanding happy.</item>
                  <item>Yea thirdly, ſuppoſing that Myſtery to have been revealed to <hi>Adam,</hi> to be beleeved, the very revelation hereof would have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, and commanded him to have beleeved it, and his belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving would have been a proper act of Obedience to the Law of that promiſe requiring faith; If therefore he had not a power to have obeyed the law of that promiſe by beleeving, then it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, That his firſt power could not have inabled him to ſtand by a Law of Works, by perfect obedience, which (as you expreſly grant) he was fully able to do.</item>
               </list>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:121088:32"/>
               <p>And yet, before paſſing from this queſtion, I mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> word to prevent the miſtaking mine and in anſwering it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> is, That I have not endeavoured to prove <hi>Adams</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aving <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> power, from this reaſon, becauſe without it God could not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice deſtroy mankinde; for whether he had a power of beleeving or no, is a Queſtion needleſſe and impertiment, touching the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ring of Gods juſtice in mans deſtruction, as may be made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſt thus.</p>
               <p>If <hi>Adam,</hi> in whom (as you acknowledge) all his poſterity ſtood, had ſuch a power, under the firſt Covenant, as was ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ent to juſtifie God in the death or deſtruction of man diſobeying then to examine, whether <hi>Adam</hi> had power to beleeve a ſecond Covenant is altogether <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>iceeſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ry to clear Gods Juſtice, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying man, diſobeying; But the former is true, this <hi>Adam</hi> had &amp;c. becauſe God after ſtating him in his firſt power, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> thereupon as a righteous Judge, fore, paſſe or denounce the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning or ſentence of death or deſtruction upon him, if he ſho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> diſobey, <hi>Gen. chap.</hi> 2. <hi>verſ.</hi> 17. <hi>Thou ſhall ſurely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ye.</hi> W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> threatning could not have been juſtly denounced againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> except his firſt power and perfection, had ſuch an anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble proportion thereto, as might juſtifie that threatning. The latter alſo, That to examine, &amp;c. is a needleſſe queſtion for clearing Gods juſtice, &amp;c. follows inevitably, becauſe ſeeing the eſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ce of <hi>Adams</hi> firſt power was ſufficient to juſtifie God in deſtroying man, diſobeying; 'tis therefore needleſſe to inquire, what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> power could produce. Yea, ſeeing you underſtand a power of beleeving, as having relation to the ſecond Covenant onely, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> therefore could not be at all neceſſary to the clearing of Gods ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice in mans death or deſtruction, becauſe the threatning of death was denounced againſt him; onely with relation to the t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> of the firſt Covenant, which alone he know; which threa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing was as juſt before Gods promiſing Chriſt in a ſecond Covenant, upon mans fall, as afterwards, becauſe God made not that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to clear his juſtice.</p>
               <p>To proceed now to the ſecond ſort of reaſonings, being on ſuppoſition, <hi>That Adam had ſuch a power, yet that this would not avail, becauſe God having made a new Govenant, &amp;c.</hi> to which I reſet. Touching which it muſt be affirmed. 1. That <hi>for God to daprive man of the bleſſing, &amp;c.</hi> As you there expreſſe, this is
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:121088:32"/>wholy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> with and deſtructive <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> of a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> of Univ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> enyes that all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to obtain Gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce or intere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e thou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>lves therein, but if we ſpeak of the Covenant of Free-Grace, them the truth is for God that he might not deprive any man of the ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſing of it, therefore to hold it forth on ſuch tearmes, as are attainable by mans improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as <hi>upon which Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>gagi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="6 letters">
                        <desc>••••••</desc>
                     </gap>ly by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, to grant acceptation and grace,</hi> (which you aſſir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the freedome of his grace) this is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and deſtructive to the very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>outh of that Covenant of grace, which con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ws ſaving grace peculiardy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> for 'twould be impoſſible for God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> not to fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, as ſhould both promiſe grace to ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ely, and not to there, (which the Covenant of grace doth) and yet alſo ſhould promiſe the ſame grace, after the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e manner, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. It muſt therefore be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the ſecond Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant are utterly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> utmoſt power, but yet this no way deſtroyes the freedome of Gods <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in that Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, for though God therein <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="6 letters">
                     <desc>••••••</desc>
                  </gap>ds <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>tai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ble conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from all, yet his promiſe wherein <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> work thoſe conditions in ſome, is of Free grace. Gods <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>t make hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of none effect. And touching your inſtance of <hi>a Noble f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ly,</hi> 'tis wholy impertinent, for all it ſhews is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t this: That the conditions required in the Covenant Gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ce, are ſuch as cannot tender all, no, n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r any one capable of grace, by his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="7 letters">
                     <desc>〈7 letters〉</desc>
                  </gap>ſt indeavour, which is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>d enviably <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>g th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of God, to work ſuch conditions in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of Free Grace, this is ſtill to be proved. By which inſtance you deny the Goſpell to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe any peculiar thing to ſome, making it onely to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the ſame conditions from all, whereas i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ed its promiſes and as large to ſome, as the command <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>'Tis then moſt ground le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, becauſe the Covenant of Grace is not common to all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>lly upon improvement, that therefore 'tis not of grace to ſome, for grace in i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is more free and tranſcend <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, becauſe to ſome onely and not to others, Which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> may be p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ed to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſo thus, <hi>viz.</hi> ſuppoſe a Prince <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> guilty of high <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſo as that without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of juſtice, he cannot but condemn them, if now lie will give <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> onely ſon, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ficed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:121088:33"/>randome for part of them, from the condemnation, becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e findes nothing in them to ſatisfie his juſtice without their deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: this betokens abundance of grace; y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> further, to work alſo in them that neceſſary condition, which he requires; becauſe they cannot attain thereto of themſelves: this is alſo a high ſtrain of Free-grace.</p>
               <p>Next follows your applying that inſtance, <hi>They that make the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving tearms of the Goſpel, &amp;c.</hi> Concerning w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> it muſt be affirmed, that in reſpect of obtaining grace to ſalvation, man by his utmoſt improvement, cannot tread as much as one ſure or ſteady ſtep in that way; ſo that his utmoſt improvement ſhall of it ſelf at beſt be ſucceſſeleſſe therein. And this is ſo far <hi>from rendring the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel reproach,</hi> as that <hi>Paul</hi> eſtabliſheth the freedome of Gods diſpenſation upon this very ground, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.16. Where after ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples given to ſet our the freedome of Gods grace, <hi>Verſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> 11. in chooſing and refuſing, according to his good pleaſure, without any regard had to any improvement or work done, be layes down this as a ſure concluſion, <hi>Verſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> 16. <hi>So then, tis not of him that wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, nor of him that runneth, but of God that ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>emeth mercy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> where <hi>Paul,</hi> that he might lay down and declare the ſure ground of ſalvation, like a wiſe builder, he firſt deſtroyes the rotten ground of the <hi>Arminians,</hi> and that by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>utting off all manner of intailement or ingagement of grace, on mans willing, yea, and running; which tearms cannot but import greateſt intention and ext<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntion of abilities: he ſaith not, upon willing or running, God hath promiſed mercy or grace, but <hi>tis not of him, &amp;c. but of God, &amp;c.</hi> The Apoſtle moſt emphatically expreſſeth it by the rearme <hi>(but)</hi> a knowne particle of oppoſition; thereby cutting off any binding of the latter, Gods mercy to the former, mans improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The reaſon of which method is clear: becauſe if it were of him that willeth or runneth, ſo as that to, and upon it, grace is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nexed, then it could not be free, and without reſpect to mans improvement; which thing <hi>Paul</hi> is proving, <hi>Verſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> 11. but muſt then have been of Grace, ingaged upon running.</p>
               <p>Touching your next expreſſion, <hi>Were I of the judgement of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minius, I could, &amp;c.</hi> I muſt with griefe of heart ſay thus much; I fear your left hand hath learned too much of this cunning; and indeed there in that enmity in the underſtanding of reaſonable man againſt the truth, that is may be more eaſie to <hi>repreſent</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:121088:33"/>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ours <hi>planſible to them,</hi> then one truth.</p>
               <p>Next followes your ſecond reaſon, upon ſuppoſing <hi>Adams</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a power of believing &amp;c. <hi>which will not juſtifie God, &amp;c. becauſe juſtice ſtands in a Geometricall proportion, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which Argument reaches far higher then the tenent it ſhould prove; yea, makes it void: For this proves not that God is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged by promiſe, &amp;c. but which is far more intolerable, this makes it but an <hi>act of juſtice in God,</hi> to give men life, or ſave them from condemnation upon improvement. For if after mans fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling from his perfect power God cannot <hi>in equity condemn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> man, doing his utmoſt,</hi> and that <hi>becauſe juſtice stands in a Geometricall proportion,</hi> or in taking an exact accompt or conſideration of the perſons preſent power and improvement, in anſwer to their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er loſt; which (according to your inſtances produced, and your direct application of all to <hi>Adams</hi> caſe) you underſtand by thoſe expreſſions of Geometricall proportion: hence then it followes, that Gods ingaging himſelf by promiſe to improvement, is no ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary ground of mans ſalvation; but Gods juſtice beholding them and their improvements, is made a neceſſary ingagement on God to ſave ſuch improvens: ſo that without ſalvation of ſuch his juſtice cannot be ſalved, and conſequently his grace needs not act in their ſalvations but for the right improvement of your Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I adde this. Mans loſing his firſt perfect power of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, &amp;c. cannot but in equity juſtifie God in his condemning man, doing his utmoſt according to his power now remaining; and that from your very reaſon, <hi>Becauſe justice ſtands in a Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metricall proportion;</hi> or in a ſtrict conſideration of perſons, their conditions, abilities, &amp;c. For if Gods juſtice ſtands in judging acts according to the abilities, where with the perſon is intruſted, then it muſt in reference hereto, count what abilities have been gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him: whereupon finding man in <hi>Adam,</hi> to have been intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted with a fulneſſe of power; to believe (which power through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out your ſecond reaſon you ſuppoſe and grant) it cannot but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire an act correſpondent: for as much therefore as man after utmoſt improvement cannot but fall infinitely ſhort of ſuch an act (which you alſo grant) Gods juſtice, upon computing both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, muſt needs be ſo far from rewarding it with grace; as that it cannot but condemne man, for acting no way anſwerable to the power given; and that in greateſt equity, becauſe of the infinite
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:121088:34"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:121088:34"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:121088:35"/>diſproportion between each, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ight <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. If Gods juſtice in judging the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, be ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> comp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ng the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, given <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> perſon in relation to the act, <hi>as that a great ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> from a m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ied <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> then two <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>iter from a widow,</hi> and that becauſe it judgeth according to their reſpective abilities; then certainly juſtice weighing ſpirituall actions, with the power given <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> (which you ſuppoſe) cannot but condemn <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, becauſe his actions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ct utmoſt improvement, hold a vaſt disprop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tion with that power.</p>
               <p>Againe, according to the parable of the talent, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f juſtice ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly requires by way of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iation, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>alout, two for two, five for five,</hi> then open r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing acts, anſwerable to the power, here ſuppoſed to be given man in <hi>Adam,</hi> it m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt needs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> man falling <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhort <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t beſt.</p>
               <p>So that indeed there is no congruity between the reaſon and the inſtances. For firſt, your reaſon is mainly grounded on this ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtion, That man had power in <hi>Adam,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> it. But the <hi>inſtances</hi> import not the leaſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ittle of my power, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the <hi>Widd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>w</hi> or <hi>Lords ſervants</hi> had and loſt.</p>
               <p>Againe, the inſtances prove it a matter of equity to accept of the endeavours of ſuch as act propo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nably to their <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> but fall infinitely ſhort of proving the acceptance of ſuch as act no way anſwerable to their talents.</p>
               <p>Which inſtances can only be parallel'd to your ſecond reaſon, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, That <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the <hi>Widow</hi> been in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſted with a great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ewdly ſpet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> all but two <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, yet thoſe m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt in juſtice have been co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ted us much as the large contributions of others; becauſe ſhe hath now no more left. And the <hi>Lords ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rva<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſing ten talents, being intruſted with one more, upon his improving that to his power, (though not well) his <hi>Lord</hi> in juſtice muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſuch improvement, and not require ſatisfaction for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>; whereas in juſt ſevei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ty, <hi>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>uſt</hi> his other <hi>ſervant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ly for not making profit of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m</hi> ſingle <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>alent,</hi> though <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> miſ-ſpent it not, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> it up.</p>
               <p>Yet I would not here be miſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, as if I conceived it matter of mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nt to ſhew your miſ-application of there inſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>; for could they be proved to be anſwerable to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> would no way advantage it; for though you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> by way
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:121088:35"/>of proofe, yet in ſo doing you pervert the uſe of inſtances, which may indeed illuſtrate a matter, but cannot prove it, according to that approved ſentence — <hi>Theologia parabolica non eſt argumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tativa;</hi> or thus, <hi>parabolae illuſtrant non probant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And touching your applying all to <hi>Adams</hi> poſterity, that, <hi>though it be ſuppoſed they had a power of believing, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Twould indeed be tedious work it to reckon up the leaſt part of all the dangerous confequences thereof; for if <hi>Adams fallen po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity may do that, which may be of more conſideration in point of equity, &amp;c.</hi> as you expreſſe. Then it followes, that mans fall is no prejudice at all, but matter of advantage rather.</p>
               <p>Againe, hence 'twill follow, that God hath no reſpect to the ſtate of the perſon acting, whether he be in a ſtate of acceptation with God, or of rejection; but only to the action done, in that man full of enmity, may do that, which may be of greater conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration in the eye of Gods juſtice, then what ſpotleſſe <hi>Adam</hi> could doe. Whereas touching the acceptance of the perſon, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the acceptance of acts, 'tis evident from the generall cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of Scripture, that the acceptance or non-acceptance of acts, principally depends on the acceptation or non-acceptation of the perſon; hence, <hi>the prayer of the wicked is an abomination to the Lord,</hi> while <hi>the prayer of the upright is his delight,</hi> Prov. 15.8. ſo <hi>God accepted Abel and his offering;</hi> Whence was his offering accepted? even from Gods free accepting the perſon, and not the perſon for the offerings ſake. But here you make God bound by equity, as much, yea more, to accept an accurſted man for his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provements ſake, then <hi>Adam</hi> a righteous man, and his righteous works: which argument directly maintaines juſtification by works and merit, in that you ſay, <hi>Man may now do what is as good or better in val<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> then Adam,</hi> who then ſtood by works.</p>
               <p>To adde yet one word againſt the force of all your Arguing, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuppoſition of <hi>Adams having a power to beleeve, &amp;c. viz.</hi> Man beinging death on himſelf by breach of the firſt Covenant, the work of juſtice hereupon is to inflict death, what ever tearmes therefore are tendered to prevent death, theſe are all fruies of free-grace: though then thoſe tearmes are unatta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>able by man fallen; God may, notwithſtanding without any injuſtice, ſuſpend the gift of a power anſwerable to them, though man periſh thereby. God was not bound in juſtice to offer any tearmes beſide thoſe to
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:121088:36"/>
                  <hi>Adam, Doe thus, elſe thou ſhalt ſurely dye,</hi> much leſſe is he bound, to give a power correſpondent to new tearms.</p>
               <p>Next followes your ſecond reaſon, <hi>If men putting forth them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, &amp;c. and not finde grace,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Touching which, I muſt affirme, that though in my former diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe I gave you no ground to think <hi>I feared your opinion to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with the opinion of Free-will</hi> in the Goſpel ſenſe, yet am I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to affirme, that the force of this ſecond reaſon, is that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry opinion which may thus be proved.</p>
               <p>If mercy putting forth their utmoſt power, and not finding grace with God, &amp;c. may be deſtroyed for want of an executive power, without any miſcarriage or ſinfulneſſe at all in the will, then men may ſo far put forth themſelves by their own power without grace, as whereby, they may be without any ſinfulneſſe at all in the will, which is indeed to have full power of Free-will. The former whereof is the expreſſe force of your reaſon; the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter alſo plainly followes; for he that can by his own power at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to a freedome from all ſinfulneſſe in his will, cannot but have Free-will to cloſe with God; becauſe without ſuch a free cloſing with God, the will cannot be free from all ſinfulneſſe: ſo than man by his own power rendring himſelf free from, or without any ſinfulneſſe at all in his will, thereby removeth all that kept him from a power of Free-will; which you afterwards grant in owning that of <hi>Augustine, Take away mans will, and take away Hell and all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againe, from the concluſion of that your ſecond reaſon, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with the former part of it, this dangerous conſequence un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidably proceeds, <hi>viz.</hi> that man is able of himſelf to remove all the ground of his condemnation, which appears thus.</p>
               <p>If the Scripture placeth Gods juſtice in condemnation alwayes, upon ſome ſinfulneſſe in the will, and man himſelf by improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be able to free himſelf from all ſuch ſinfulneſſe; then man is able of himſelf to remove all the ground of his condemnation, or to ſave himſelf from deſtruction by his own improvement, not needing grace to ſalvation. The former, that Gods juſtice is clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from the ſinfulneſſe of the will, you prove from Scripture. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, that man can render himſelf free from all ſuch ſinfulneſſe; this is the main ſtrength of your reaſon. The concluſion therefore neceſſarily followes, that man hath power to take away or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:121088:36"/>the ground of his condemnation. For if God in juſtice can only deſtroy man for ſuch ſinfulneſſe; then man freeing himſelfe from all ſuch ſinfulneſſe, takes away thereby all juſt ground of condemnation; and ſo layes a ſure ground for ſalvation, which is only oppoſed by ſin.</p>
               <p>And touching thoſe many Texts inſuing, what they prove is granted, which is, that <hi>mans condemnation is laid upon ſome ſinful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the will;</hi> but theſe are all far from proving, that man hath power to free himſelf from all the ſinfulneſſe of the will, the ſcope of all which is to ſet out the obſtinacy of the will, in the wicked actings thereof, which is a point diſtinct from that of ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the main ground of its continuing ſo perverſe: For, there is no neceſſity of ſhewing, that man wants power to ſubdue the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſeneſſe of his will in every place, where that perverſeneſſe is ſpoken of: the grounds therefore of ſuch perverſeneſſe muſt be ſought for there, where the Holy Ghoſt diſtinctly expreſſeth it: one ſpeciall place for which, <hi>John</hi> 6.36. compared with <hi>Verſe</hi> 44. &amp; 65. was proved to be in the diſcourſe given you. But yet among thoſe many Scriptures, I ſhall take notice of one, which you main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ground upon; which is <hi>Acts</hi> 7.51. which you thus alleage and open.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ye have alwayes reſiſted; now how did they reſiſt, &amp;c. not by any defectiveneſſe of power, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whereas 'tis cleare that the former part of the <hi>Verſe</hi> layes down the ground of their perverſeneſſe firſt, as the precedent article of their condemnation, in this clauſe, <hi>ye uncircumciſed in heart;</hi> whence indeed their <hi>reſiſting</hi> aroſe; ſo that the queſtion is, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they had power to take away this main obſtacle, <hi>the uncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion of their hearts;</hi> but 'tis certaine they cannot; for this is peculiarly within Gods power, as <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.6. <hi>The Lord thy God will circumciſe thy heart.</hi> Seeing then they reſiſt from the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſion thereof, it followes, that they reſiſt through want of power, for that they need power from above to circumciſe their hearts.</p>
               <p>And ſo all thoſe other Texts prove not at all mans not want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a power, &amp;c. From all which you would force in this tenent, That man wants no power to reduce his will to Gods, which is to ſay he hath a power of Free-will, as appears from that, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.51. whence you ſay, <hi>Man reſiſts not from any want of power;</hi> the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:121088:37"/>ſelfe-ſame from <hi>John</hi> 5.40. <hi>Ye will not come, they wan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> not pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to come:</hi> though it be proved in the diſcourſe given you, that the reaſon thereof is declared to be a want of power, in <hi>Chap.</hi> 6.44.</p>
               <p>Next you raiſe a Quere, <hi>how your opinion differs from the opinion of Free-will?</hi> Which Quere I finde you make from this ground, becauſe <hi>your opinion is feared to comply with the Arminian tenent of Free-will,</hi> as you expreſſe ſoon after the beginning of this clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sermon. Touching which, what I did, &amp; do fear and finde is this; that your fifth and main <hi>aſſertion</hi> impleaded, is the ſame with that Arminian Maxime, there expreſt, <hi>facienti quod in ſe est, &amp;c.</hi> Which opinion you take to be that of Free-will; and ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed you may, for both are the ſame in effect: For if man may ſo do as to ingage God to give grace (which you affirme) he doth thereby that which is as ſurely effectuall to ſalvation; as Free-will to act ſavingly: for God cannot but performe what he hath p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to man upon doing. And that this your opinion is the grand tenent of the <hi>Arminians,</hi> may be proved by the teſtimony of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor <hi>Robert Sanderſon, in his firſt Sermon,</hi> ad populum, <hi>on</hi> 3 <hi>Kings</hi> 21.29. § 26. where he hath this paſſage.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It appears from the premiſes, that Gods thus dealing with wick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d &amp;c. gives no warrant or strength at all, either to that popiſh or cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt doctrine of</hi> Meritum congrui, <hi>in deſerving the firſt grace, by the right uſe of naturals, or to that rotten principle and foundation of the whole frame of Arminianiſme,</hi> facienti quod in ſe eſt, Deus non poteſt, non debet denegare gratiam.</p>
               <p>Which latter is your very opinion; for, <hi>if man may do ſuch things as whereupon God hath promiſed to give grace</hi> (which you affirm) then man may ſo do, as <hi>wherupon God neither ought nor can deny grace;</hi> becauſe God for his truth and faithfulneſſe ſake, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can, not ought to violate his owne ingagements; ſo that by maintaining your fifth aſſertion, as a tenent ſo neceſſary, you up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the <hi>rotten foundation of the whole frame of Arminianiſme.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame alſo may be further proved out of Dr. <hi>Twiſſe</hi> his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute about Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> and <hi>Arminius,</hi> where <hi>Sect.</hi> 2. <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>upon the ſixth errour,</hi> Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> charges the Arminian School<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>men, with this very tenent thus, <hi>Si faseret, De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> adjuvants, quod in ſe eſt, Deus illum illuminaret ſupernaturali gratia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yea further, leſt it be thought, the <hi>Arminians</hi> may be wronged, <hi>Arminius</hi> himſelf repeats this very tenent, more plainly, in his
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:121088:37"/>reply immediately following; yea, which is very conſiderable, he labours to prove it after that very manner, as you doe, by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king God ingaged by promiſe, as in theſe words.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Annon iſto dicto Chriſti, babenti dabitur, promiſſio iſta contin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, qua Deus ſpondet ſe gratia ſupernaturali illuminaturum, qui lumine naturali recte utetur, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t ſalt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> utetur minus male.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which text, <hi>to him that hath ſhall be given, Arminius</hi> produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth, inſtead of thoſe Texts of yours, <hi>ask and you ſhall have, &amp;c.</hi> whence he affirmes the ſame with you, ſaying, that <hi>by that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, to him that hath ſhall be given; God ingages himſelfe to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten with ſupernaturall grace, ſuch as rightly uſe naturall light, or at leaſt; who will uſe it, as much as he can, leſſe evilly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that touching the great difference you make between your opinion, and that of Free-will, as if yours were not Arminian, 'tis plain, <hi>Arminius</hi> holds the one as ſtrongly as the other: yours op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, he plainly holds, and labours ſo to prove it, as you do; for inſtead of perfect free-will, he acknowledgeth ſome defect in the will, as by that his expreſſion, <hi>leſſe evilly,</hi> whereby granting ſome ſinfulneſſe therein.</p>
               <p>Yea, that <hi>Arminius</hi> holds both opinions; how contradictory ſoever to each other, I finde expreſly in Doctor <hi>Twiſſe, in his third book and first digreſſion,</hi> touching the ſenſe of that Text, <hi>to him that hath ſhall be given,</hi> as appears by this ſentence. <hi>Quamvis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirant gratiam ad r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>te <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>dum naturalibus, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>amque ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralem, tam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rerd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> diſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>inem iſta natura vipra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>are poſſe,</hi> which he there proves from <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rvinu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>:</hi> It appeats there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore from theſe teſtimonies, that your opinion of <hi>ingaging God to give grace, &amp;c.</hi> which you go about to quit them from, is moſt uſuall amongſt them, being more plauſible; and that which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies a neceſſity of ſupernaturall grace, is but rarely found among them.</p>
               <p>And touching your complyance with both theſe opinions, as their former is your fifth aſſertion, ſo the latter of Free-will in the gro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt ſenſe, is directly maintained, by the force of your ſecond reaſon, as is before proved.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, ſeeing you profeſſe your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd in all, to be the <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ning of ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſſions, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> are given by the most a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Arminians (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> diſcourſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d of this Sermon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> intimated</hi>) it ſeems meet to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>quaint you, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow greatly you
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:121088:38"/>have croſt your own deſigne, and that by the ſecond and maine point of difference, which you make between your opinion and theirs. For whereas you there charge them with this, as their main and only tenent, <hi>viz. That man hath power to produce a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving act, without any ſupernaturall aſſiſtance,</hi> it appears from thoſe words preſcript; <hi>Quamvis requirant gratiam, &amp;c. ſupernatura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem;</hi> that when they are their Crafts-maſters, they do, and that generally, require ſupply of ſupernaturall grace; ſo that you ſeem uncharitably to take them alwayes at the worſt.</p>
               <p>In which alleaging of theſe teſtimonies, though I cannot but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge my prolixity, yet muſt I partly juſtifie it, from the neceſſity thereof, even to eſtabliſh that truth by the mouth of two or three witneſſes, which being only affirmed before, you did ſo lightly put by.</p>
               <p>And yet muſt I adde one word, to minde you of your politick method, uſed about denying your tenent to be <hi>Arminian;</hi> that whereas their opinion of Gods being ingaged, &amp;c. (given in thoſe words, <hi>facienti quod in ſe eſt, &amp;c.</hi>) is directly yourfifth aſſertion; and their main maxime you wholly neglect to prove, wherein your opinion differs from that maxime, contenting your ſelf only to ſhew how it differs from another Arminian opinion, which you were not at all charged with: ſo that ſtill your opinion lyes under this heavie charge, of being <hi>the main<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> foundation of the whole frame of Arminianiſme,</hi> which is now made good by clear evidence.</p>
               <p>Next you raiſe a queſtion touching <hi>the difference between an exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutive and willing power, or a principle drawing out that power in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to act, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The occaſion of your opening which diſtinction, I finde to be from a paſſage in my diſcourſe given you; where 'tis denied, that man hath an executive power to believe, which now you would farther prove.</p>
               <p>In opening of which power you ſeem to contradict yourſelf, for you take it to be a power, whereby to act, and yet by thoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, you underſtand that to be an executive power, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not inable to act: you ſay <hi>A rich man hath an executive power to be liberall, whilſt of a penurious diſpoſition, though by that power he is never the nearer being liberall:</hi> but how contradictory is it to ſay, A man by means of ſuch a thing, hath power to ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap> ſuch a worke, though by that thing be is never the nearer execution
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:121088:38"/>thereof; by this you ſeem to nullifie that power in reſpect of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abling to an act, which you call a power to act.</p>
               <p>Again, you ſay he hath an executive power to do, though that power be defective touching doing, but that which is defective in order to an act, cannot be a power to act, for a power to act is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with defectiveneſſe, or want of power; power and want of power are contraries.</p>
               <p>But for brevity ſake, I ſhall endeavour to grant the utmoſt extent of your inſtances, <hi>viz.</hi> A penurious rich man hath ſuch a power in him, in order to acts of liberality, as an Infant hath principles of reaſon and underſtanding, which may of themſelves in an ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry way of nature, become executive to anſwerable acts, without any ſuper-naturall infuſion; ſo a rich penurious man hath ſuch principles as by conſideration, councell, &amp;c. may be inclined to liberality, without a ſuper-naturall change of thoſe principles, but yet whilſt penuriouſly diſpoſed, he is as far, or farther, from an executive power, as a willing; as a child is in the caſe given.</p>
               <p>And thus may the reſt be underſtood, <hi>As that Gen.</hi> 31.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9. <hi>'tis in the power, &amp;c.</hi> that is, he had a ſufficiency of outward ſtrength and ſuch a naturall principle of revenge, as might act revenge, if not hindered by an extraordinary hand, and ſo, <hi>have not I pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to eate, &amp;c.</hi> man hath a naturall receptive faculty for that end.</p>
               <p>The tenour of which inſtances being thus conſidered, the maine is to examine; what is in them to ſerve your purpoſe, which is to prove, that a man hath an executive power to beleeve: Between which inſtances, and the things you would prove, there is as vaſt a diſ-proportion, as between naturall and ſupernaturall acts, for all that theſe prove, is but that men have an executive power to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme ſuch acts, as may be done without ſupernaturall influence, as <hi>to be liberall, to frequent the Ordinances,</hi> or (to ſpeak in your own language) <hi>to ſin, revenge, eate, drink, &amp;c.</hi> Now 'twere moſt unadviſed to conclude, becauſe men have an executive power to the externall acts of Religion, frequenting the Ordinances; to acts naturall, eating, drinking; morall, as to be liberall, &amp;c. that therefore they have a like power to ſupernaturall acts. Of all which inſtances, the moſt genuine ſcope, is to prove mans free-will to beleeve, for the main Argument of both your Sermons, is touching mans power towards attaining faith, which power
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:121088:39"/>you call executive, which ſo called, you demonſtrate by making it like that power which thoſe inſtances hold forth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> but to all thoſe ſeverall acts, the perſons reſpectively have a power of free will; thoſe concerning men have, becauſe all thoſe acts may be done by man in his pure naturalls, thoſe which concern God are much more within his power to will, as they are acts requiring power, for God is not capable of receptive power (though God wills not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ring acts) therefore in making mans executive power to come to Chriſt, or beleeve, to be ſuch as thoſe inſtances have, you neceſſarily make man to have Free-will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o beleeve, elſe all thoſe inſtances are to no purpoſe.</p>
               <p>In briefe thou a man cannot be ſaid to have an executive power to any act, but what he can voluntarily do, and is within the li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of that power, ſo as to ſtand in need of no ext<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ordinary divine aſſiſtance; 'tis contradictory to ſay an executive power cannot execute of it ſelfe, for if a ſupernaturall power muſt co-operate to execution, then the other power cannot be executive, but the work of faith cannot be executed, without a divine power infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed (which you elſe-where grant) therefore man cannot have an executive power to beleeve, till he be ſo inſpired; inſteed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of a <hi>willingneſſe to draw out an executive power to act faith</hi> which you ſpeak of there muſt be a putting in a new power, before any drawing out to act can be.</p>
               <p>To and this therefore, I deſire to know directly what this pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is by name, which you call executive, for it forms not imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that the name <hi>executive</hi> ſhould be any other then a nick name of ſuch a power as cannot execute. Who ever then can diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh between an executive power, or a principle whereby to act, (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>syo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mit) and ſuch a principle as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> produce a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>act, ſuch a one will doubtleſſe out the hair indeed.</p>
               <p>But yet between your unfolding the diſtinction of powers, you inſert two particulars, one is a quaere about <hi>Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>s, which is for ſubſtance the ſame with your opening the diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ce, between your opinion, and that of free will, which being already <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ale with, I paſſe over.</p>
               <p>The other particular is an Objection from <hi>Joh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>:</hi> 44. Which in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> given you, is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llendged, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> through was of power; which for anſwer, you <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>; Now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> come<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="63" facs="tcp:121088:39"/>put forth himſelf in any ſuch way, wherein God hath promiſed to meet him with grace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By which expreſſion, <hi>No man can come,</hi> you underſtand can proceed ſo far in a way of nature, in order to grace, as wherein God hath promiſed to meet him with grace; but this deſtroyes the ſenſe, for 'tis moſt evident, that the expreſſion <hi>cometh</hi> imports a coming to life with ſaving grace, which might be proved from many other Texts, ſome whereof are given in that diſcourſe, as <hi>John</hi> 5.40. ſo <hi>John</hi> 6.37. <hi>He that cometh to me,</hi> which imports coming with ſaving faith; which place you have underſtood ſo. Now there is a great contrariety between theſe, for mans doing that wherein God hath promiſed to meet him with grace, is a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by himſelf without grace; upon which doing, you ſay, God meets with grace; but the comming here is a ſaving comming, or unto life by ſaving grace; therefore not a comming in the courſe of naturall abilities, to meet with grace thereupon.</p>
               <p>Againe, there appears not the leaſt ground for ſuch an interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, becauſe here is never a word ſpoken of pawing forth in a courſe of nature, but of comming to Chriſt, or believing (which in the diſcourſe given, are proved to be tearms equivalent) nor yet is there the leaſt tittle of a promiſe of meeting man with grace upon comming.</p>
               <p>And for that clauſe, <hi>except my Father draweth,</hi> which you ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound, <hi>except be interpoſe with ſome greater power then ordinary's</hi> that you underſtand thereby, Gods inabling to improve naturals to the utmoſt, in order to grace, is plaine, in that you make Gods interpoſing to be a <hi>carrying of man ſo far in a courſe of nature, as wherein God hath promiſed to meet him with grace,</hi> and ſo you make Gods drawing to be, but by way of preparation unto grace, promiſed thereupon; againſt which 'tis evident, 'tis ſuch a draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as whereby man commeth unto Chriſt, or believeth both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one; therefore drawing is an act of divine power, working ſaving-grace, and not a carrying of man ſo to do, as upon which doing, God will afterwards meet him with the gift of grace. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards you adde another Expoſition, <hi>no man hath any foreſight of any compleat power of comming;</hi> which implyes, man hath in himſelf a power to come to Chriſt, before Gods drawing; ſo that by drawing; God only gives him ſight of that power: But this directly oppoſeth the words which are, <hi>no man can</hi> or <hi>hath a
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:121088:40"/>power to come;</hi> he ſaith not, no man hath a ſight that he can come.</p>
               <p>For eſtabliſhment of which expoſition, you re-aſſume your di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of powers already dealt with; by opening of which executive power to come to Chriſt, you make mans power of comming to Chriſt, or believing, to be a power of Free-will, as is before proved from the inſtances.</p>
               <p>After that, you expreſly conclude from what is delivered in that Sermon, <hi>The neceſſity of your fifth aſſertion, touching Gods promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing grace, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Concerning all which, to ſpeak truly ſuppoſing theſe two Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments (which you ſay <hi>are for the clearing of the whole buſineſſe</hi>) were unanſwerable, yet would they be far from ſuch a <hi>clearing;</hi> for all the arguing of Men or Angels ſhall never prove this, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out bringing a promiſe of God for it; which throughout this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon you no where attempt, though all your former texts preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to containe ſuch promiſes alleaged in your former Sermon, are prowed wholly impertinent, in that diſcourſe given in. The thing you would prove by theſe Arguments is, That God is inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by promiſe to naturall improvers; but if this promiſe be ſuch as <hi>God hath been graciouſly pleaſed to make</hi> (which you affirme) then you cannot prove ſuch a promiſe by Argument, but only from expreſſe exhibition; becauſe what God doth of Free-grace, can proceed from no ground or reaſon, but his own freeneſſe, for which, being Gods eſſence, no reaſon can be given.</p>
               <p>Yes, of all grounds, that whereon you build the ſtrength of all your Arguments; namely, the vindication of <hi>Gods juſtice,</hi> muſt needs be moſt weak: it ſeems of all reaſonings moſt abſurd, to ſay God cannot but freely promiſe grace, becauſe his juſtice binds him to it. And ſeeing you expreſſe your <hi>maintaining that aſſertion to be of ſo great neceſſity for upholding the truth, &amp;c. of the Goſpel.</hi> I wonder you omit, both the juſtifying it, by any one Scripture, after all the Scriptures alleaged are proved contrary; and likewiſe the vindicating it from thoſe pernicious conſequences, which in the diſcourſe given you, are ſhewed to be moſt inevitably deduceable thence; becauſe in what degree that ſuffers, whereon you make the <hi>truth, grace, &amp;c.</hi> to depend; ſo much muſt the <hi>truth, grace, and uprightneſſe of the Goſpel, &amp;c.</hi> ſuffer.</p>
               <p>And touching that of <hi>Auguſtine, take away, &amp;c.</hi> if it be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with a paſſage immediately foregoing, which is, that men
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:121088:40"/>may be deſtroyed without any malignancy in their wils, both put together, plainly make man to have power of Free-will; for you make taking away all malignancy of will to be within mans pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, which being taken away, nothing hinders from Free-will.</p>
               <p>Next you further refer this controverſie to your <hi>disputes againſt the Arminians;</hi> diverſe things, wherein eſpecially in the two laſt Exerciſes, ſeem juſtly liable to exception, but I ſhall decline fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dealing there with on this ground, becauſe the ſubſtance there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is repeated in this Sermon: and though I intended to have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a word about that Text, <hi>To him that hath ſhall be given,</hi> I ſhall wholly omit it, referring to that learned diſcourſe of Doctor <hi>Twiſſe</hi> upon the <hi>ſenſe thereof,</hi> in his <hi>Third Book</hi> fore-cited.</p>
               <p>Touching <hi>the uſe</hi> you make of all, in which is implyed your great care in all this, <hi>to ſtudy out mollifying, and to prevent harſh expreſſions, which</hi> (as you intimated in diſcourſe) <hi>are given out by most againſt the Arminians;</hi> I may not unfitly inſert a paſſage which you uſed againſt the Arminians, being here fitly applicable, <hi>viz. While you go out of the Kings high-way in relation to Free-grace, and ſeek out by-wayes</hi> of mans ingaging God by improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, cenſuring Gods juſtice, the freeneſſe of his grace, &amp;c. <hi>you hereby fall into worſe wayes,</hi> though you endeavour ſo to pave them, that they may ſeem moſt ſmooth.</p>
               <p>And whileſt you profeſſe great care againſt <hi>harſh unſavoury ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, &amp;c.</hi> I know not what expreſſions can be more harſh then ſuch, as belch out ſuch calumny againſt <hi>the justice of God, the freeneſſe of his grace, &amp;c.</hi> of which it may fitly be ſaid, <hi>who art thou that replieſt againſt God?</hi> nor know I with whom ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions can be ſavoury after triall, except with the <hi>Arminians</hi> themſelves.</p>
               <p>And touching your Apology, I commend this <hi>Quare</hi> to ſerious conſideration, whether it would not be a more ingenuous way of Apologizing to diſclaime your own errour, and with that mouth to juſtifie that truth wherby you have condenmed it, rather then to pleaſe your ſelf with this ſaying. <hi>If ſo be we cannot come to expreſſe our ſelves, &amp;c. We ſhall content our ſelves with ſome ſuch manner of excuſe as this is, That God hath not given us that ability and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of utterance and expreſſions, and that we conceive the buſineſſe better in our mindes, then we are able to give account of to others?</hi> Which I the rather refer to conſideration, becauſe of that <hi>fluency
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:121088:41"/>of utterance and expreſſion,</hi> which God hath vouchſafed you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove many.</p>
               <p>And ſeeing you conclude, <hi>The Scripture affords ſuitable expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions for this matter, and that ſuch are here moſt neceſſary,</hi> I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der you omit ſearching out ſuch from Scripture; and inſtead thereof take upon you ſo hard a task, as to create or frame Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, or promiſe of grace, out of <hi>reaſon</hi> and <hi>argument,</hi> without any Scripture-proof.</p>
               <p>And touching your advice, cloſing up all; ſeeing in my former diſcourſe I endeavoured <hi>to pleade for the truth of God.</hi> I have in this endeavoured (according to Gods aſſiſtance vouthſafed) <hi>to quallifie that hardneſſe,</hi> which your Arguments have attempted to caſt upon it.</p>
               <p>Yet one word more, touching your ſcope in propounding and maintaing your fifth aſſertion, ſeeing you hold it ſo neceſſary for the encouraging of naturall men, I wonder you wholly omit to teach them what particular duties are to be done by them in this way of improvement: For whileſt you tell them, <hi>If they put forth themſelves to do what God hath inabled them in a way of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, they may do ſuch things as whereunto God hath promiſed grace,</hi> you neglect to tell them what thoſe things are. Now you know, <hi>Dolus latet in generalibus,</hi> deceit lyes in generals; and therefore in the iſſue ſuch generall tearms muſt needs become ſnares of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit to naturall men, who after doing ever ſo much, are ſtill left to ſeek out what actions they be, upon which God hath promiſed grace, which tearms (to retort upon you with your own language) are indeed <hi>like to the demanding to catch all the fiſhes in the ſea, or foules of the aire;</hi> or like the leading men into a Laby<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inth, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the middle of the boundleſſe Ocean, and there leaving them: For you give naturall men a boundleſſe task of doing ſuch things as whereto God hath annexed grace by promiſe; but what or how many thoſe things are, is not at all ſhewed, but is left to their own judgement; which being wholly erroneous, muſt neceſſarily lead them to preſumption or diſpaire. Much like in ſome reſpect to the doctrin of many heretofore, urging in generall a neceſſity of le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall terrou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, before any true comfort could be had, by which means multitudes have laid lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ds of per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> upon themſelves one after another; and after all, find<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> no more ground com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort then at the beginning, becauſe they can ſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e not Scripture
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:121088:41"/>Standard to meaſure ſuch qualifications by. Seeing then you count this doctrine <hi>(of naturall mens doing ſuch things as whereupon God hath promiſed grace)</hi> ſo neceſſary; you may do well in a matter ſo weighty, not to lead and leave them to be beguiled by generals; but let them know in particular, what, and how many actions they are to do, upon doing whereof God hath promiſed grace; that ſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they have finiſhed ſuch a tale, they may ſing a <hi>Quietus eſt</hi> to their ſoules through confidence of their happy ſtate, as the <hi>Papiſts</hi> do, upon their <hi>Opus aperatum,</hi> after they have mumbled over the full <hi>tale</hi> of their <hi>prayers,</hi> according to the number of their <hi>Beads.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now in anſwer to your method, I ſhould ſhut up all with a word of uſe, which may be firſt for caution to ſuch as take up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them to promote the truth of God, <hi>viz.</hi> foraſmuch as errour is of ſo bewitching a nature, as that men are apt to maintain one errour by the broaching of others worſe, rather then to relinquiſh and diſclaim the firſt, this ſhould provoke ſuch perſons in ſpeciall, to great jelouſie againſt every errour, leaſt one errour received prove an in-let to more and worſe.</p>
               <p>Or ſecondly, by way of direction to men, both in improving the meanes of grace, and in tryall of their ſtate.</p>
               <p>Firſt, then for direction in improving; firſt negatively, let no man becauſe he labours, in the ſtrength of his naturalls, to improve the outward meanes of grace, therefore addreſſe himſelf to God, with this confidence; Lord I have endeavoured with utmoſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, &amp;c. Therefore do thou, according to thy promiſe made to theſe improvements, give me ſaving grace, for this is to miſt in lying vanities, and to go to God with a lye in ſteed of a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, becauſe God hath made no ſuch promiſe; but contrarily, in all thine improvements, acknowledge with thankfulneſſe Gods long ſuffering, and freedome of diſpenſation, who might in juſtice have hurld thee from out of the womb, the place of thy ſinfull conception, into hell the place of endleſſe woe, as he hath done multitudes; and may now juſtly leave thee in all thy improvements, to go with the <hi>five fooliſh Virgins to the gate,</hi> through which the <hi>wiſe Virgins entred in,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd yet ſhut thee for ever out of the bride chamber; nevertheleſſe waite thou in Gods preſcribed way, abhorring thy ſelf in all thine endeavours, as being ſo far from ingaging God to give grace, as that the loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomeneſſe of them all may juſtly provoke God for ever to ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend his grace from thee.</p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:121088:42"/>
               <p>Again, in point of tryall, ſing not this <hi>requiem</hi> to thy ſoul, I have earneſtly laboured to reach the terms of the Covenant of Grace, therefore certainly God hath added thereto the work <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> faith, becauſe otherwiſe the Goſpell <hi>could not be a Covenant of Free-Grace;</hi> but contratily, examine whether the powers of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in thee, be ſo carried up above themſelves, by divine operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as that they renounce, and abhor thy moſt choyce improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as having no worth, no comfort in them, and in ſteed thereof do cleave vigorouſly, and intirely unto Chriſt, as the onely fountain of all true comfort; yea, all this done ſo, as in ſteed of finding matter of ſelf-boaſting in thine own improvements, thou findeſt great ground of admiring the free diſpenſation of Gods over-powring grace, working ſuch a change in thee, contrary to, &amp; above thy ſelf; this being found may afford much comfort. But I muſt totally, though moſt abruptly, decline further progreſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="postscript">
               <opener>
                  <salute>Sir,</salute>
               </opener>
               <head>Poſt Script.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>HAving laid by this Work of Vindication for diverſe moneths, and that in hope of commending it, in ſome most convenient time, to your peruſall, and finding after ſo long expectation, multiplicity of occaſions, more and more flowing in unto you to the greater diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of ſuch your convenient leiſure, as I hoped for, poudring withall the ſo great importance of this matter, ſo greatly concerning the doctrine of the Gospel, to which as ſupream, ſubordinate matters of order and diſcipline, ought to give the right hand of pre-eminence: I count it my duty without further delay, to crave both your peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall therof, as alſo your impartiall care and zeal to vindicate a truth ſo choyce and fundamentall, ſo far forth as it hath been defamed, that ſo after my being made by accident, an</hi> occaſioner <hi>of your</hi> defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming truth, <hi>viz. by my former diſcourſe, I may by this be made the</hi> occaſioner <hi>of your</hi> vindicating <hi>the ſame; and that you alſo (who after your most ſolemn under-taking to deſtroy the</hi> Arminian <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, have laid again the main foundations thereof, and ſo accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to</hi> Pauls <hi>expreſſion,</hi> have made your ſelf a tranſgreſſor) <hi>may no longer continue ſo to be, by upholding thoſe rotten principles. Which ſervice for truth, in all bumility, and reſpect committing to your timely performance, as you are a pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mover of truth, I devote my ſelf ſteafastly to continue.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Tuus uſque ad Aras veritatis SAMUEL LANE.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix__tract">
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:121088:42"/>
            <head>Certaine Reaſons alleaged to prove the Souls enjoying CHRIST after death, before the Reſurrection, And that againſt theſe three enſuing errours.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>That the Scripture ſpeaks nothing of the ſtate of the Souls from Death to the Reſurrection.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>That it no where declares the Soules happy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> glorious ſtate from Death to the Reſurrection.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>That the Soule is mortall and dyeth with the body.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>ABout which, I ſhall only alleage one proof, <hi>viz.</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 6, 7, 8. Whereof a word touching the coherence. The Apoſtle having in the foure firſt Verſes ſpoken of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> eternall houſe in Heaven,</hi> and of their <hi>gor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing to be clothed upon</hi> therewith, laying down <hi>v.</hi> 5. two grounds to prove that they ſhall be clothed therewith, &amp; teſtifying that aſſurance, <hi>v.</hi> 6. <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we are alwayes confident;</hi> he proceeds in the middle of <hi>v.</hi> 6. to diſcuſſe the happineſs of the ſoule after death, as alſo his deſire thereof. <hi>Knowing that being preſent in the body we are abſent from the Lord,</hi> and conſequently that our preſence therein is matter of diſadvantage, which he proves by the reaſon annexed, <hi>v.</hi> 7. <hi>For we walk, &amp;c. viz.</hi> whileſt in the body: <hi>by faith,</hi> or by believing the <hi>glory</hi> to come, the <hi>things not ſeen,</hi> as in <hi>cap.</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> ult. <hi>And not by ſight, i. e.</hi> a beatificall viſion of glory. And thus the teams <hi>walk</hi> deſcribes glory to come, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.4 <hi>Shall walk with me in white.</hi> Yea thus alſo our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with, and beholding God, are put together, <hi>Iohn</hi> 17.24. <hi>May be with me and behold, &amp;c.</hi> Implying, that when our ſtate is changed from being preſent in the body, and abſent from the Lord, as <hi>v.</hi> 7. into an abſence from the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and preſence with God, as <hi>v.</hi> 8. <hi>then we ſhall walk by ſight.</hi> And that this is fully implyed appears, becauſe the not walking by ſight is alleaged to prove abſence from God, and therefore contrarily, preſence with him muſt argue walking by ſight. Next in <hi>v.</hi> 8. he further inlarges upon the former, beginning thus, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which may well be rendred <hi>we are confident therefore:</hi> or from thoſe grounds foregoing, namely, the diſadvantage of our preſent ſtate expreſt, &amp; the advantage of the future implyed. And thus the conjunction <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is elſewhere uſed, for which of many places ſee eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.18. where tis <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>the therefore that feareth;</hi> for though ſome tranſlations omit <hi>therefore,</hi> yet the ſenſe neceſſarily requires it; becauſe that laſt clauſe is a concluſion drawn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from the major, or main propoſition beginning the <hi>Verſe; There is no feare in love, therefore he that feareth, &amp;c.</hi> It followes, <hi>And we are willing</hi> or approve rather, <hi>to be abſent out of the body &amp; preſent with the Lord,</hi> of two ſtates preferring the better: And ſo he doth <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.23. <hi>Deſtring to depart and to be with Chriſt, which is far better?</hi> better then what; ſee <hi>v.</hi> 22. then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o <hi>live in the fleſh</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> All which may be ſumm'd up thus; as we know that in ſtead of our earthly houſe diſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lved, we ſhall be clothed upon with one eternall, which we gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> after<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, ſo we know that in the mean time, that is to ſay, the time of the ſoules abſence from the body,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:121088:43"/>we ſhal be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> with the Lord, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y. Which being t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> opened, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Friſt againſt the firſt error, <hi>viz. That the Scripture ſpeaks nothing of the ſtate of the ſoul from death to the reſurrection,</hi> and that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>: If the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſtate of the ſoul when abſent from the body, then the Scripture declares what the ſtate therof ſhal be a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ter death unto the Reſurrection. But the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer is true, that the Scripture declares the ſtate of the ſoul when a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ent from the body, for <hi>Paul</hi> confidently concludes, it ſhal then be preſent with the Lord. The Fat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er therfore, that the Scripture declar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> what the ſtate of the ſoul ſhall be after death, &amp;c. is as evident; becauſe there being no time where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſoul can be abſent from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ody, beſides the time between death and the Reſurrection; therefore what the Scripture ſpeaks of the ſoul as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſent from the body, can concern only the ſtate of the ſoule between death and the Reſurrection, at which reſurrection the ſoule becomes preſent in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy againe.</p>
            <p>The ſecond errour following upon the former, <hi>viz. That the Scripture <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> where declares the happy or glorious ſtate of the ſoul from death to the reſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="8 letters">
                     <desc>〈8 letters〉</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> may be thus deſtroyed. If the Scripture doth determine the ſtate of the ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from death to the reſurrection, to be more deſirable the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of the ſoul before death, living by faith, then 'tis certain that the Scripture de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares the ſtate of the ſoul happy after death. But the former, that the Scripture doth determine the ſtate of the ſoul, &amp;c. i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> true: for the Apoſtle expreſly deſires that ſtate, which ſhall be when the ſoul in abſent from the body, rather then the life of faith in the body. The latter the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, that the Scripture concludes the ſtate of the ſoul to be happy after death follows in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>evitably; becauſe as the ſtate thereof when abſent from the body by death, could not be more deſirable then living in the body by faith, except it were more happy; ſo being the more happy of the two, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s therefore tran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="8 letters">
                  <desc>〈8 letters〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly happy in it ſelf; becauſe that ſtate which is leſſe happy, even the life of faith, is throughout the Scripture declared a happy &amp; bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ed ſtate in it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if the ſoul from death to judgement ſhall be preſent with God, the certainly the ſtate thereof ſhall be a ſtate of glory. But the former, that the ſoul ſhall be then preſent with God, <hi>Paul</hi> is moſt con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ident of. The latter therefore, that this ſhall be a ſtate of glory, followes clearly, becauſe the ſtate of glory is throughout the Scripture deſcribed to be a being <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with the Lord,</hi> or <hi>walking with,</hi> or <hi>being with the Lord,</hi> or with the Lambe, as frequently throughout the <hi>Revelation,</hi> ſo 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.17. <hi>Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 7.14.</p>
            <p>Yea thirdly, if the ſoul after death ſhall ſee that glory, the things eternall, &amp;c. which in the body it only apprehends by faith, then certainly the ſtate thereof after death ſhall be a ſtate of glory. But the former is fully implyed as is before clearly proved. The latter therefore, that the ſtate thereof af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter death ſhall be a ſtate of glory, followes neceſſarily; becauſe the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture frequently makes the ſeeing or beholding Gods glory, to be the ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and eminent effect of the ſtate or glory: for which, beſides <hi>Ioh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 17.24. fore-mentioned, ſee <hi>Matth.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.20 <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.14. <hi>Rev.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>2.4. Yea further, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſeeing of his glory cannot but transforme th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> beholders into a ſtate of glory according to that, 1 <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 3.2 <hi>We ſhall be like him, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> we ſhall ſee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> as he is:</hi> So 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>upon beholding</hi> (by faith) <hi>we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ged much more ſeeing God as he is.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:121088:43"/>
            <p>And whereas it may be here objected, and that truly, That the Scripture alleaged in the two laſt reaſons, do refer to the ſtate of glory at the Reſurrection, and not to any ſtate preceding; yet becauſe the ſtate of the ſoul when abſent from the body is here deſcribed by theſe very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>ſeeing and being with the Lord,</hi> which elſewhere deſcribe the perfect ſtate of glory, therefore both ſtates muſt needs be the ſame in nature or quality, (though not in degrees) both having the ſelf ſame deſcription.</p>
            <p>The third errour, <hi>That the ſoul is mortall and dy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> with the body,</hi> muſt f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll, if the Arguments againſt the former errour be avail<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>able: for if the ſoul be happy after death, then not mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>all. But yet I ſhall adde one Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt this third errour, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the ſoul when abſent from the body ſhall be preſent with the Lord, as really as 'tis preſent in the body before death, then certainly the ſoul dyeth not with the body.</p>
            <p>But the former, that the ſoul when abſent, &amp;c. is true; for the Apoſtle expreſſeth the preſence of the ſoul with the Lord, by that very word where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he expreſseth the preſents of the ſoul in the body, both which therfore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port a like reall preſence. The la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er therfore, that the ſoul dyeth not with the body, followes neceſſarily; becauſe as the ſoul cannot have exiſtance or be preſent in the body except it lives there, ſo much leſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e can it be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with God, <hi>that quickneth all things</hi> (1 Tim. 6.13) except it lives with him. Seeing then the ſoul is preſent with the Lord as living (after abſent from the body) therefore it dyeth not with the body.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object </seg>
               </label> But poſſibly ſome may ſay; you under<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ke to prove the ſtate of the ſoul from that Scripture, which doth not at all mention the ſoul.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw </seg>
               </label> For anſwer; though the ſoul be not expreſſed, yet that the ſtate of the ſoul is meant there, is moſt evident; becauſe there is an apparent diviſion made between ſoul o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> body, both in <hi>v.</hi> 6. <hi>We being preſent in the body;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is expreſt both the body, and we preſent in it. And againe <hi>v.</hi> 8. there is a body, and then we to be abſent from it, and preſent with the Lord; which <hi>we</hi> being to expreſſe <hi>Paul</hi> and other Believers, muſt of neceſſity be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of their perſonall eſsence; but their corporall eſsence it cannot be, for the body is expreſt beſides in both Verſes: by <hi>we</hi> therefore muſt needs be meant the ſoul, as appears undeniably; becauſe there is nothing beſides the body that can be of the eſsence of man but the ſoul alone. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when the Scripture ſpeaks diſtinctly of an humane perſon, it divides him into theſe two parts, <hi>Soule and Body;</hi> ſo <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.28. or <hi>into minde and fleſh,</hi> ſo <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. ult.</p>
            <p>Secondly, another Argument might be urged from that clauſe, <hi>we w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lk by faith,</hi> if compared with the Context; which clauſe <hi>by faith</hi> holds forth the proper act or ſtate of the ſoul before death (<hi>for with the heart man believes,</hi> Rom. 10.10.) though ſoul be not expreſt; and ſo <hi>v.</hi> 8. holds forth the act and ſtate of the ſoul to come after death, though ſoul be not expreſt there.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object </seg>
               </label> But there is yet another Objection, <hi>viz.</hi> That the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſet day of recompenſing every man according to what he hath done, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10. and many like places; and therefore it ſeemes contradictory, that the ſoul ſhould at all partake of that recompence before the ſet time.</p>
            <p>For anſwer, though the Scripture denominate the day of judgement
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:121088:44"/>to be the great day of recommence; yet this proves not that the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> of men are altogether excluded from glory and wrath till then, becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Scripture doth frequently aſcribe the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er denomination of a work <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the laſt accompliſhmention, or finiſhing of it though much of the work be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> before: to clear which, for brevity lake, I will only inſtance in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of Scripture touching this ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y day of recompence. which is called <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.30. <hi>the day of redemption:</hi> now as that cannot be underſtood <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively, as if the Saints receive no part of their redemption till th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> moſt evident 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. that the Saints do in a degree pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> really <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> redemption here, by being <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> their vains <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>ſation through</hi> the <hi>pretious blood of Christ;</hi> but 'tis therefore call'd the day of redemption, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe then ſhall be the conſummation thereof, both in ſoul and body, the body being then raiſed, which therefore is called diſtinctly in R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>. 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>3. <hi>the redemption of the body.</hi> So is it alſo the day of recompence, not excluſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as if God conferred no happineſſe on the ſoul till th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, but becauſe then the happineſſe ſhall be perfected; ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the glory of that rec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ce, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſhall be ſo tranſcendent, as that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e which the ſoul ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ean time, may in compariſon of that m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt perfect re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, be counted as no recompence, according <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that paralell expreſſion 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.10. <hi>Even that which was made glorious, had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> glory, &amp;c.</hi> In the manner this day of redemption is called <hi>the ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> as in that <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Waiting for the adoption, the redemption of our body;</hi> not that the Saints <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> not of adoption till the redemption of their bodies, for in <hi>verſ.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>6.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, they are expreſly ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wed to be the <hi>ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ted ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s of</hi> God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the ſpirit,</hi> and 1 <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the ſons of God,</hi> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent priviledge. So that the perfect poſseſſion of that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="6 letters">
                  <desc>••••••</desc>
               </gap>ance of Gods ſons, whereto they are adop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ted in called adoption, as it act<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ally accompl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth the priviledges of adoption, though they be really adopted before.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Ja. Cranford.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
